<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="correction"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BMJ-UK</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bmj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The BMJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0959-8138</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1756-1833</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5930353</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">correction1162</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.k1954</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Corrections</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effectiveness of a childhood obesity prevention programme delivered through schools, targeting 6 and 7 year olds: cluster randomised controlled trial (WAVES study)</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>361</volume><elocation-id>k1954</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Published by the BMJ Publishing Group Limited. For permission to use (where not already granted under a licence) please go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://group.bmj.com/group/rights-licensing/permissions">http://group.bmj.com/group/rights-licensing/permissions</ext-link></copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>BMJ</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmj.k1954.pdf"/></article-meta></front><body><p>Several acknowledgments and funding details were omitted from this paper (BMJ 2018;360:k211, doi:<related-article id="d35e67" related-article-type="corrected-article" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1136/bmj.k211">10.1136/bmj.k211</related-article>) by Adab and colleagues. The authors would like to thank their collaborators at the Institute of Metabolic Science at the Medical Research Council (MRC) Epidemiology Unit (University of Cambridge) for their support and assistance, particularly Soren Brage, Kate Westgate, and Stefanie Hollidge, for training of field staff on use and maintenance of Actihearts, for overseeing data preparation, and for analysis and interpretation of the physical activity data; Timo Lakka (principal investigator of the PANIC study, University of Eastern Finland) for sharing exercise data in a similarly aged cohort of children to allow translation of observed heart rate into activity energy expenditure; staff who are working, or have previously worked, at the Nutrition Epidemiology Group in Leeds, who have supported the trial team in terms of administration of the CADET food tick list and processing of the data to enable us to undertake dietary intake analysis, in particular Neil Hancock, Cristina Cleghorn, Meagan Christian, Jayne Hutchinson, Holly Rippin, and Catherine Rycroft. Ulf Ekelund, Soren Brage, Kate Westgate, and Stefanie Hollidge were funded in part by the MRC (MC_UU_12015/3) and the National Institute for Health Research Biomedical Research Centre, Cambridge (IS-BRC-1215-20014).</p></body></article>