<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Pediatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Pediatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Pediatr.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Pediatrics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-2360</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6308200</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fped.2018.00393</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pediatrics</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Childhood Overweight and Obesity and Associated Factors in Iranian Children and Adolescents: A Multilevel Analysis; the CASPIAN-IV Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khashayar</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kasaeian</surname><given-names>Amir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heshmat</surname><given-names>Ramin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>Mohammad Esmaeil</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mahdavi Gorabi</surname><given-names>Armita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Noroozi</surname><given-names>Mehdi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7"><sup>7</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/565317/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>Mostafa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8"><sup>8</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9"><sup>9</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/496531/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>Roya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10"><sup>10</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c002"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Chronic Disease Research Center, Endocrinology and Metabolism Population Sciences Institute, Tehran University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Center for Microsystems Technology, Imec and Ghent University</institution>, <addr-line>Ghent</addr-line>, <country>Belgium</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Hematology-Oncology and Stem Cell Transplantation Research Center, Research Institute for Oncology, Hematology and Cell Therapy, Tehran University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Hematologic Malignancies Research Center, Research Institute for Oncology, Hematology and Cell Therapy, Tehran University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Pediatrics, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Ahvaz</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Department of Basic and Clinical Research, Tehran Heart Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><sup>7</sup><institution>Social Determinants of Health Research Center, University of Social Welfare and Rehabilitation Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><sup>8</sup><institution>Non-communicable Diseases Research Center, Alborz University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Karaj</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="aff9"><sup>9</sup><institution>Endocrinology and Metabolism Research Center, Endocrinology and Metabolism Clinical Sciences Institute, Tehran University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="aff10"><sup>10</sup><institution>Department of Pediatrics, Child Growth and Development Research Center, Research Institute for Primordial Prevention of Non-communicable Diseases, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Isfahan</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Angie Jelin, Johns Hopkins University, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Geert 't Jong, University of Manitoba, Canada; Khyzer Bin Izhar Aziz, The Johns Hopkins Hospital, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Mostafa Qorbani <email>mqorbani1379@yahoo.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Roya Kelishadi <email>roya.kelishadi@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Obstetric and Pediatric Pharmacology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Pediatrics</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>393</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Khashayar, Kasaeian, Heshmat, Motlagh, Mahdavi Gorabi, Noroozi, Qorbani and Kelishadi.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khashayar, Kasaeian, Heshmat, Motlagh, Mahdavi Gorabi, Noroozi, Qorbani and Kelishadi</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><bold>Objective:</bold> The purpose of this paper is to explore multidimensional factors related to childhood obesity and overweight based on the data gathered on different aspects of the general health status were assessed among a large number of Iranian children and adolescents in the fourth phase of the &#x0201c;Childhood and Adolescence Surveillance and Prevention of Adult Non-communicable disease&#x0201d; survey. It also aims to determine the degree to which each ecological context contributes to childhood overweight/obesity.</p><p><bold>Method:</bold> A total of 14,880 students and their parents were recruited. They filled out a questionnaire on their relationship with peers, body image, and psychosocial environment of school, dietary habits, life-style habits, physical activity pattern and socioeconomic status (SES). Their height, weight, was measured and body mass index (BMI) was calculated. Obesity and overweight was defined based on the WHO growth chart. Multilevel modeling using three-level random intercept logistic regression models were used to assess predictors of overweight and obesity. In our hierarchical models, children (first level) were conceptualized as being nested within provinces (second level) and provinces within quad regions (third level).</p><p><bold>Result:</bold> From among the 13,486 recruited students, 9.7% were overweight and 11.9% were obese. In multivariate model (adjusted model), being boy (OR:1.58), living in urban area (OR:1.58), having positive family history of obesity (OR = 2.04), breakfast skipping (OR: 1.46), socioeconomic status (OR <sub>moderateSES/lowSES</sub> = 1.44 and OR <sub>highSES/lowSES</sub> = 1.89), and birth weight (BW) (OR <sub>normalBW/lowBW</sub> = 1.33 and OR <sub>highBW/lowBW</sub> = 1.8) were associated with childhood obesity. Increasing age was the only factor in the obesity model that had a significant preventive effect on the odds of becoming obese (OR = 0.96, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). In multivariate model, living in urban area, increasing age, high and moderate SES, high BW and family history of obesity were the significant predictors of overweight.</p><p><bold>Conclusion:</bold> Our findings show that high BW, sociodemographic characteristics, breakfast skipping, and family history of obesity are associated with childhood obesity and overweight. Therefore, developing strategies that consider the effects of diverse sociodemographic and environmental factors on childhood overweight and obesity would be the most effective way to prevent and manage this multifactorial health concern.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>obesity</kwd><kwd>overweight</kwd><kwd>body mass index</kwd><kwd>multilevel analysis</kwd><kwd>socioeconomic status</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="48"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="5646"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Over the past decade, a considerable surge is noted in the prevalence of childhood obesity in different parts of the world, raising concerns about the negative health consequences of the condition in the long run (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>According to the reports released by WHO European childhood obesity surveillance initiative 2008, the prevalence of obesity ranged from 6.0 to 26.6% among boys and from 4.6 to 17.3% among girls (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>Many studies have identified the influential factors for childhood obesity through examining simple relationships between childhood obesity and the predictors such as polygenic, metabolic, psychosocial, behavioral, and environmental (obesogenic) factors with focus on leisure time activity, food intake (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). This is while it is well-known that childhood obesity is the result of a multifactorial etiology involving individuals and environmental factors, adding that effective interventions for prevention and control of childhood obesity should be considered for different factors (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In other words, childhood obesity could only be tackled through a multidisciplinary approach in three levels: family, school and community but there is a need to identify the elements which are amenable to measurement and interventions in each level (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p><p>On the other hand, most of the studies on obesity determinants have been conducted in North America where obesity was first described as a social problem. This is while obesity has recently been recognized as an emerging public health concern worldwide (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Based on the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention's (CDC) criteria, a recent systematic review estimated the overall prevalence of obesity and overweight in Iran to be about 5.1% [95% confidence interval [CI], 4.4&#x02013;5.8] and 10.8% (95% CI, 10.2&#x02013;11.4), respectively (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). It suggested that despite the fact that the prevalence of childhood obesity in the Iranian children is not considerably high, but the escalating trend of excess weight among young children is alarming and thus more interventional programs are needed in this regard.</p><p>In the fourth phase of the &#x0201c;Childhood and Adolescence Surveillance and Prevention of Adult Non-communicable disease&#x0201d; (CASPIAN) survey, different aspects of the general health status were assessed among a large number of Iranian children and adolescents (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The purpose of this paper, therefore, is to explore multidimensional factors related to childhood overweight and obesity based on this data, and to determine the degree to which each ecological context contributes to childhood overweight/obesity.</p><p>This information will be useful for the design and planning of intervention program through facilitating the identification of areas requiring analysis, major issues and priorities for tackling the obesity epidemic in the country.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>The fourth phase of the CASPIAN was conducted in 2011&#x02013;2012 among a national representative sample of Iranian students from both urban and rural areas. Similar to previous phases, this national school-based surveillance aimed to study the risk behaviors and risk factors of chronic non-communicable diseases using global school-based health survey (GSHS). The study protocol has been published elsewhere (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>In brief, students from different grades were selected through multistage, cluster sampling method from 31 Iranian provinces. Clusters were determined at the level of schools, resulting in 10 sample units (students and their parents) in each cluster and 48 clusters in each province. The maximum sample size that could give a good estimate of the risk factors of interest was selected. Thus, a total of 14,880 students and their parents were recruited.</p><p>The CASPIAN study questionnaires (student and parent questionnaire) were based on the GSHS and was prepared in Persian. The validity and reliability of these questionnaires were confirmed previously (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The students' questionnaire included questions about demographic characteristics (age, sex, and living area), food and meal consumption habits, life-style habits, physical activity, screen time pattern, and genetic determinants (family history of hypertension, diabetes, obesity). Past history of the student birth weight (BW) and family dietary habits to the student were included in the parents' questionnaire.</p><p>Oral assent was obtained from participants, and written informed consent was obtained from their parents and the study was approved by ethic committee of Isfahan University of Medical Sciences (Project code: 294176).</p><sec><title>Definition of Terms</title><p>Breakfast consumption was assessed using a single question, &#x0201c;usually on how many days of the week do you eat breakfast?. Breakfast frequency was defined as skippers (eating breakfast 0&#x02013;4 days/week), and non-skippers (eating breakfast 5&#x02013;7 days/week) (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Food habits including fruit intake, vegetable intake, and sweetened beverages were assessed using a single questions, &#x0201c;how many times do you eat each of these food groups?.&#x0201d; Response options were daily, weekly, seldom and never. For statistical analysis food habits considered as daily and non-daily consumption.</p><p>Screen time was assessed using a single item, &#x0201c;how long students spent their time on watching television, video and using computer in weekdays and weekends.&#x0201d; According to the international screen time recommendations, screen time &#x0003c;2 h/day was considered as low, and 2 h/day or more was considered high (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Physical activity was assessed using two questions. (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) During the past week, on how many days you have physically activity for 30 min per day? (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) How many hours do you spend in sport class in school per week? Physical activity was categorized into tertiles. The first tertile was defined as low, second tertile as moderate and third tertile as high.</p><p>The methods and variables used for calculating socioeconomic status (SES) were based on the categories approved in the Progress International Reading Literacy Study (PIRLS) for Iran (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Socioeconomic status (SES) was calculated using principal component analysis (PCA). Using this method, variables such as parental education, parental occupation, possessing private car, school type (public/private), and having personal computer in home were summarized in one main component. This main component was then categorized into tertiles (low, intermediate, and high SES).</p><p>Students' BW was asked from parents and was categorized as low BW (LBW) (BW &#x0003c;2,500 g), normal BW (NBW) (BW: 2,500&#x02013;4,000 g) and high BW (HBW) (BW &#x0003e; 4,000 g).</p><p>The height, weight of the students were measured under standard protocols and by using calibrated instruments. Body mass index (BMI) was calculated by dividing weight (kg) to height squared (m<sup>2</sup>) and then categorized based on the WHO growth charts (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Childhood overweight and obesity is defined as a BMI between 85th and 95th and &#x02265; 95th percentile for children of same age and sex, respectively (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>As the data of one of the provinces was not available, the analysis was performed on information from the other 30 provinces. Mean of continuous variables was reported with 95% of the confidence interval (CI). Categorical variables were expressed as numbers and percentages. Continuous variables such as age, and BMI across regions were compared using ANOVA test. The homogeneity of categorical variables such as SES, sex, and residency area across quad regions were examined by Chi-square test.</p><p>Multilevel modeling was also used for data analysis as it adequately represents the unexplained variability of the nested structure, which is often hard to depict in the single-level approach (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Taking into account the hierarchical structure of our dataset and the possible correlation within and between clusters, we used a three-level random intercept logistic regression models for overweight and obesity. In our hierarchical models, children (first level) were conceptualized as being nested within provinces (second level) and provinces within quad regions (third level).</p><p>We assessed the evidence for the effects of several predictors on overweight and obesity. First, the unadjusted effects of the predictors on overweight and obesity were studied in the univariate model. Thereafter those with effects at the 0.2 level of significance were entered to enter the multivariate model. This information helped us study and compare their adjusted effects and effect size on the outcomes of interest.</p><p>The results of logistic regression models were presented as odd ratio (OR) and 95% CI. All statistical measures were estimated using survey data analysis methods.</p><p>All data management procedures were done using Stata 11.2 (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Univariate and multivariate modeling were performed using hierarchical modeling methods using Package &#x0201c;lme4&#x0201d; in R software version 3.3.1 (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). All the variables with a <italic>p</italic>-value at or below 0.2 in the univariate analysis were included in the multivariate analysis. <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered as statistically significant.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s4"><title>Results</title><p>Overall, 13,486 students aged 6&#x02013;18 years-old out of the 14,880 invited ones participated in this study. The participation rate of the study was 90.6%. Totally 6,846 (50.76%) of them were boys and about 75.6% of them were from urban areas. Mean age (SD) of all participants were 12.46 (3.35) years. Overall, 8.89 and 7.64% of them were categorized in low and high BW group. Family history of obesity was reported by 45.47% of the participants. Being involved in regular physical activity was reported by 24% of the boys and 13% of the girls. Only 9% of the participants did not report being engaged in any physical activity. Overall, 32.8 % (28.39% of boys and 35.89% of girls) of students were breakfast skipper (eating breakfast &#x0003c;5 days/week. Daily consumption of fruits, vegetables and sweetened beverages was reported by 55.74% (58.07% of girls and 53.47% of boys), 35.84% (37.36% of girls and 34.35% of boys), and 20.12% (17.60% of girls and 22.57% of boys) of students, respectively.</p><p>The demographic characteristics of the students according to study regions is outlined in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The distribution of all demographic characteristics (age, sex, living area, and SES) was statistically different between regions (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the anthropometric indices of study population according to study regions. Overall, 9.7% of the students (10.1% of girls vs. 9.3% of boys) were overweight and 11.9% (10.1% of girls vs. 13.6% of boys) were obese. Mean of BMI and prevalence of overweight and obesity in the second highest SES region was significantly higher than other regions (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Individual level characteristics among population by regions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Demographic characteristics</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Study regions</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Central (<italic>n</italic>: 3827)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>North-northeast (<italic>n</italic>: 2359)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Southeast (<italic>N</italic>: 1181)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>West (n: 6119)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total (<italic>n</italic>: 13486)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>2</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.44 (3.35)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.49 (3.23)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.49 (3.43)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.45 (3.40)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.47 (3.36)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>1</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boy</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014 (52.63)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1189 (50.40)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">552 (46.74)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3091 (50.51)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6846 (50.76)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>&#x003c8;</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Girl</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1813 (47.37)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1170 (49.60)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">629 (53.26)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3028 (49.49)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6640 (49.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living area<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>1</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3226 (84.30)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1712 (72.57)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">651 (55.12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4602 (75.21)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10191 (75.57)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>&#x003c8;</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">601 (15.70)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">647 (27.43)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">530 (44.88)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1517 (24.79)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3295 (24.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SES<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>1</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">764 (21.48)2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">747 (33.54)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">580 (54.21)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2056 (37.13)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4147 (33.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1281 (36.02)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">681 (30.58)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">289 (27.01)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1849 (33.39)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4100 (33.09)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>&#x003c8;</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1511 (42.49)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">799 (35.88)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201 (18.79)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1632 (29.47)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4143 (33.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SES, socioeconomic status</italic>.</p><fn id="TN1"><label>1</label><p><italic>Are presented as n (%)</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>2</label><p><italic>Is presented as mean (SD)</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN3"><label>&#x003c8;</label><p><italic>Using Chi<sup>2</sup> Test</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN4"><label>&#x02020;</label><p><italic>Anova Test</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Anthropometric measures of study population according to study region.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Anthropometric measures</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="6" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Study regions</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Central (<italic>N</italic> = 3,827)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>North-northeast (<italic>N</italic> =2,359)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Southeast (<italic>N</italic> = 1,181)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>West (<italic>N</italic> = 6,119)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total (<italic>N</italic> = 1,3486)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>1</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.06 (18.92, 19.20)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.17 (18.99, 19.36)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.82 (18.71, 18.93)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.66 (17.41, 17.90)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.85 (18.78, 18.93)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN6"><sup>2</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.99 (11.94, 14.10)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.91 (12.53, 15.37)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.47 (10.67, 12.30)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.29 (4.96, 7.86)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.89 (11.34, 12.43)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>&#x003c8;</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN6"><sup>2</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.52 (9.54, 11.50)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.72 (9.47, 11.97)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.43 (8.69, 10.16)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.86 (4.49, 7.22)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.66 (9.16, 10.16)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>&#x003c8;</sup></xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>BMI, body mass index</italic>.</p><fn id="TN5"><label>1</label><p><italic>Is presented as mean (95% CI)</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN6"><label>2</label><p><italic>Are presented as prevalence (95% CI)</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN7"><label>&#x003c8;</label><p><italic>Using Chi-square Test</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN8"><label>&#x02020;</label><p><italic>ANOVA Test</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec><title>Multilevel Modeling Results</title><p>The associated factors of childhood obesity in univariate and multivariate hierarchical models is presented in Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. In the obesity univariate modeling, all the predictors, except for consumption of sweetened beverage and physical activity met the criteria (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.2) and were included in the multivariate model. In the multivariate model, being boy (OR: 1.58), living in urban area (OR: 1.58), having positive family history of obesity (OR = 2.04), breakfast skipping (OR: 1.46), SES (OR moderate SES /low SES = 1.44 and OR high SES/low SES = 1.89), and BW (OR NBW/LBW = 1.33 and OR HBW /LBW = 1.8) were associated with childhood obesity. Increasing age was the only factor in the obesity multivariate model that had a significant preventive effect on the odds of becoming obese (OR = 0.96, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Associated factors of childhood obesity in hierarchical multilevel models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Variable</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Obesity</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Univariate models (unadjusted)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Multivariate model (unadjusted)</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OR (S.E.)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic>-value</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OR (S.E.)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (boy/girl)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 (0.05)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living area (urban/rural)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 (0.07)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 (0.09)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.01)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.01)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SES (Moderate/low)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57 (0.08)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 (0.09)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SES (high/low)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21 (0.08)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89 (0.09)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breakfast consumption (skipper/non-skipper)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweetened beverage intake (daily/non-daily)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 (0.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fruit intake (daily/non-daily)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetable intake (daily/non-daily)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity (moderate/low)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.425</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity (high/low)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.07)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.459</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screen time (high/low)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (0.08)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birthweight (2.5&#x02013;4 kg/ &#x0003c; 2.5 kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 (0.11)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 (0.12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.017</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birthweight (&#x0003e;4 kg/ &#x0003c; 2.5 kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93 (0.14)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80 (0.15)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family history of obesity (yes/no)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SE, standard error; SES, socioeconomic status. Bold values are significant in level of 0.001</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In the overweight univariate hierarchical modeling, all the predictors, except for daily consumption of sweetened beverage, vegetable intake and physical activity met the criteria (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.2) and were included in the multivariate model. In the adjusted model, living in urban area (OR: 1.5), increasing age (OR: 1.04), high and moderate SES (OR moderate SES /low SES = 1.23 and OR high SES/low SES = 1.70), HBW (OR HBW /LBW = 1.39) and family history of obesity (OR: 1.17) were the significant predictors of overweight (Table <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Associated factors of childhood overweight in hierarchical multilevel models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Variable</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Overweight</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Univariate models (adjusted)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Multivariate model (adjusted)</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OR (S.E.)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic>-value</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OR (S.E.)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (boy/girl)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.07)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.278</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living area (urban/rural)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 (0.08)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 (0.10)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.01)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.01)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SES (Moderate/low)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 (0.08)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 (0.09)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.026</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SES (high/low)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86 (0.08)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70 (0.09)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breakfast consumption (skipper/non-skipper)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (0.07)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.081</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweetened beverage intake (daily/non-daily)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.412</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fruit intake (daily/non-daily)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.07)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.980</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetable intake (daily/non-daily)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.784</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity (moderate/low)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.07)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.574</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity (high/low)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.08)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.709</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screen time (high/low)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.07)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.08)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.626</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birthweight (2.5&#x02013;4 kg/ &#x0003c; 2.5 kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.156</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 (0.12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birthweight (&#x0003e;4 kg / &#x0003c; 2.5 kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 (0.15)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 (0.16)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.040</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family history of obesity (yes/no)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.07)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.015</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SE, standard error; SES, socioeconomic status. Bold values are significant in level of 0.001</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s5"><title>Discussion</title><p>The worrying upward trend in childhood obesity is changing it into a serious and urgent health issue, and thus policymakers in different parts of the world are concentrating on various educational, medical and public health interventions designed to attenuate its growth (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). The best way however to develop and implement an effective strategy is to really understand the condition.</p><p>While most of the existing literature focuses on single-component interventions, more recent studies suggest defining the &#x0201c;toxic environment&#x0201d; in which the children live in, and determining an intervention model that integrates activities in more than one setting to ultimately reduce obesity and its complications more effectively (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p><p>Health behaviors associated with childhood obesity are shaped by multiple factors; as family and school are considered as the main ecological environment surrounding children, adopting health initiatives through a multi-level approach that connects parents and care givers in schools would help fight the multifactorial nature of childhood obesity (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Mohammadpour-Ahranjani et al. similarly reported that the causes of childhood obesity, which is growing in Iran likewise many other countries, are perceived to relate to macro-level policy influences, the school environment, sociocultural factors, and family and individual behavioral factors, acting in combination (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>In line with previous studies, especially those from Iran, this study showed high prevalence of childhood obesity in Iran (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Our results also suggested that the factors that explained the variation in children's weight status were mainly consistent with those reported in previous research on childhood obesity and generally with theoretical reviews on weight gain and its pathways (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Having higher BW and being born to overweight or obese parents are both considered to increase the risk of childhood obesity (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Moreover, in line with previous studies, breakfast skipping was associated with childhood obesity in our study (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)</p><p>As for the influence of the living area, controversial results are reported. Several studies have reported a higher prevalence of obesity among rural children compared with their urban counterparts (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). It is plausible that lower levels of awareness on nutrition and health, lesser access to healthier food and the availability of fewer exercise facilities in rural regions and probably due to lower income levels is the cause. Our study, surprisingly, reported students from urban areas to be at a higher risk of the condition. In our case, the current shift to the westernized lifestyle, especially the intake of attractive energy dense food with undesirable composition, increased consumption of animal fats and sugars and reduced consumption of dietary fiber, along with lack of sufficient physical activity, happening mainly in the urban areas may be the reason (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). This trend has been responsible for the significant increase in the number of overweight and obese children in the past two decades.</p><p>Similarly, the relation between SES status and the higher risk of obesity varies according to social environments and context. In developing countries children from lower SES families are reported to be at significantly greater risk of becoming overweight/obese (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Many researchers consider intake of high-calorie and low-nutrition foods such as consuming junk foods or unhealthy foods or limited time and access to resources for physical activity as the main determinants of childhood obesity (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). This is while our results, similar to other studies in developing countries showed higher SES status to be associated with higher risks of obesity (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). This again could be because of the rapid growth of the westernized lifestyle in our country. Our results also failed to show any link between following a diet rich in nutritional foods, such as fruit/vegetables, adequate intake of beverages such as milk and fruit and vegetable juice, and engagement in physical activity to decreased risk of childhood overweight/obesity (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Limitations</title><p>The present study managed to identify various factors influencing childhood weight during school when children start to be exposed to an environment other than their family. However, we did not take into account the school grade in which the students were studying in and thus the effect of duration of exposure to these external factors is missing. Moreover, all the ecological contexts and parameters that could somehow influence childhood obesity, such as quantity and quality of physical education at school level and home, school nutrition program, and school resources (e.g., playgrounds), were not studied. The influence of contextual factors at the community level, such as the availability and accessibility of a safe park or playground, accessibility to healthy food in the community, and also walkability was not studied either. As a result, the current study was mainly focused on individualized and family factors and failed to identify school and community factors linked with childhood obesity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s7"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our findings show a high prevalence of childhood overweight and obesity in Iranian children and adolescents and high BW, sociodemographic characteristics, breakfast skipping, and family history of obesity are associated with this health concern. Therefore, developing strategies that consider the effects of diverse sociodemographic and environmental factors on childhood overweight and obesity would be the most effective way to prevent and manage this multifactorial health concern. The results of the present study thus may help policymakers to provide a theoretical basis and model childhood obesity as a function of both individual and external factors deriving from both family and school.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>MQ, RK, and RH designed the research. MM and AM conducted the research. AK and MN analyzed the data. PK, AK and MQ wrote the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karnik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanekar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Childhood obesity: a global public health crisis</article-title>. <source>Int J Prev Med</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 22506094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22506094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>KMV</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Incidence of childhood obesity in the United States</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>370</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1309753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24476431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wijnhoven</surname><given-names>TMA</given-names></name><name><surname>van</surname><given-names>Raaij JMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rito</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hovengen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunesova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>WHO European childhood obesity surveillance initiative 2008: weight, height and body mass index in 6-9-year-old children</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Obes.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2047-6310.2012.00090.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23001989?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23001989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherburne</surname><given-names>Hawkins S</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A review of risk factors for overweight in preschool children: a policy perspective</article-title>. <source>Int J Pediatr Obes.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>209</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17477160600943351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17907326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stafford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellaway</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Macintyre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pathways to obesity: identifying local, modifiable determinants of physical activity and diet</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>1882</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2007.05.042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17640787?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17640787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Childhood Obesity: Causes and Consequences</collab></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/obesity/childhood/causes.html">https://www.cdc.gov/obesity/childhood/causes.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Azizi-Soleiman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Controlling childhood obesity: a systematic review on strategies and challenges effective interventions for prevention and control of childhood obesity should be considered for different aspects</article-title>. <source>J Res Med Sci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>993</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1008</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25538786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammadpour-Ahranjani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashidi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Adab</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Contributors to childhood obesity in Iran: the views of parents and school staff. Public Health</article-title> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>128</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2013.10.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haghdoost</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadeghirad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Khajehkazemi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Trend in the prevalence of obesity and overweight among Iranian children and adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>393</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>400</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nut.2013.08.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24332523?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24332523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardalan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ataie-Jafari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahreynian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Taslimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Methodology and early findings of the fourth survey of childhood and adolescence surveillance and prevention of adult non-communicable disease in Iran: the CASPIAN-IV study</article-title>. <source>Int J Prev Med.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 24498502?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24498502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Majdzadeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Heshmat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aminaee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardalan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development and evaluation of a questionnaire for assessment of determinants of weight disorders among children and adolescents: the Caspian-IV study</article-title>. <source>Int J Prev Med.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>705</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 23112896?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23112896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahadi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahedi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Association of breakfast intake with psychiatric distress and violent behaviors in Iranian children and adolescents: the CASPIAN-IV study</article-title>. <source>Indian J Pediatr</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>922</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12098-016-2049-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26935200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Academy of Pediatrics, Committee on Public Education</collab></person-group>
<article-title>American Academy of Pediatrics: children, adolescents, and television</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>107</volume>:<fpage>423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.107.2.423</pub-id> Ogle, Laurence T.; Sen, Anindita; Pahlke, Erin;<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogle</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pahlke</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jocelyn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kastberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Roey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<source>International Comparisons in Fourth-Grade Reading Literacy: Findings from the Progress in International Reading Literacy Study (PIRLS) of 2001</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ERIC</publisher-name> (<year>2003</year>). p. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heshmat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghoreshi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Djalalinia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabatabaie</surname><given-names>OR</given-names></name><name><surname>Safiri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of socioeconomic status with psychiatric problems and violent behaviours in a nationally representative sample of Iranian children and adolescents: the CASPIAN-IV study</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source> (<year>2016</year>) 6:e011615. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2016-011615</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27531729?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27531729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>WHO</surname><given-names>Multicentre Growth Reference Study Group</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>WHO child growth standards based on length/height, weight and age</article-title>. <source>Acta Paediatr Suppl.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>450</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08035320500495548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16817681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokdad</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recent trends in waist circumference and waist-height ratio among US children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source> (<year>2006</year>) 118:e1390-8. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2006-1062</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17079540?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17079540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Multilevel Statistical Models</source>. <publisher-loc>Chichester, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name> (<year>2011</year>). p. <fpage>358</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>StataCorp</collab></person-group>
<article-title>2009</article-title>. <source>Stata Statistical Software: Release 11</source>. <publisher-name>College Station, TX</publisher-name>: <publisher-name>StataCorp LP</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R</surname><given-names>Core Team</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>R: a Language And Environment For Statistical Computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna</source> (<year>2013</year>). Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org">www.R-project.org</ext-link> (Accessed Oct 18, 2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e4;chler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Fitting linear mixed-effects models using lme4</article-title>. <source>J Stat Softw</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v067.i01</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eneli</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Severe childhood obesity: an under-recognised and growing health problem</article-title>. <source>Postgrad Med J.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>639</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/postgradmedj-2014-133033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26338983?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26338983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelsey</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaepfel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjornstad</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadeau</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Age-related consequences of childhood obesity</article-title>. <source>Gerontology</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>222</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000356023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24434909?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24434909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>De</surname><given-names>Ferranti SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Majdzadeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>O</surname><given-names>'dea JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Adeli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Childhood obesity: today and tomorrow's health challenge</article-title>. <source>J Obes.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>208392</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/208392</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24324881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24324881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dooyema</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Belay</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Foltz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanck</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The childhood obesity research demonstration project: a comprehensive community approach to reduce childhood obesity</article-title>. <source>Child Obes.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>454</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/chi.2013.0060</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24094146?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24094146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khashayar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heshmat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Aminaee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardalan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Metabolic syndrome and cardiovascular risk factors in a national sample of adolescent population in the middle east and north africa: the CASPIAN III study</article-title>. <source>Int J Endocrinol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>702095</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/702095</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23476647?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23476647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehrkash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammadian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mousavinasab</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Obesity and metabolic syndrome among a representative sample of Iranian adolescents</article-title>. <source>Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>756</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 23077856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23077856</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baygi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorosty</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asayesh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansourian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Determinants of childhood obesity in representative sample of children in North East of Iran</article-title>. <source>Cholesterol</source> (<year>2012</year>) 2012: 875163. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/875163</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22844585?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22844585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azadbakht</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Saraf-Bank</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardalan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Heshmat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The association of birth weight with cardiovascular risk factors and mental problems among Iranian school-aged children: the CASPIAN-III study</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>150</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nut.2013.06.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24206820?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24206820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Djalalinia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heshmat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardalan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazyar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of breast feeding and birth weight with anthropometric measures and blood pressure in children and adolescents: the CASPIAN-IV study</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Neonatol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>324</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedneo.2015.01.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25892644?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25892644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ejtahed</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Heshmat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasani-Ranjbar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziaodini</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Taheri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of parental obesity with cardiometabolic risk factors in their children: the CASPIAN-V study</article-title>. <source>PloS ONE</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e0193978</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0193978</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29641604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29641604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shafiee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Taheri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardalan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of breakfast intake with cardiometabolic risk factors</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>575</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jped.2013.03.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24029551?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24029551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahadi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardalan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Asayesh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between breakfast intake with anthropometric measurements, blood pressure and food consumption behaviors among Iranian children and adolescents: the CASPIAN-IV study</article-title>. <source>Public Health</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>129</volume>:<fpage>740</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2015.03.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26043966?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26043966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Urban-rural differences in childhood and adolescent obesity in the United States: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Child Obes.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/chi.2014.0085</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25928227?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25928227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harun</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Probst</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Urban-Rural Differences in overweight status and physical inactivity among US children aged 10-17 Years</article-title>. <source>J Rural Health</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>407</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-0361.2008.00188.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19007396?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19007396</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>Pour M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarraf-Zadegan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadry</surname><given-names>G hossein</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Alikhassy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Obesity and associated modifiable environmental factors in Iranian adolescents: Isfahan Healthy Heart Program - heart health promotion from childhood</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Int.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12911481?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12911481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Childhood overweight, obesity, and the metabolic syndrome in developing countries</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Rev</source>. (<year>2007</year>)<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/epirev/mxm003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bahreynian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heshmat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardalan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of growth disorders in a nationally representative sample of Iranian adolescents according to socioeconomic status: the CASPIAN-III Study</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Neonatol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedneo.2014.12.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25603727?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25603727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bahreynian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasaeian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardalan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Weight disorders and anthropometric indices according to socioeconomic status of living place in Iranian children and adolescents: the CASPIAN-IV study</article-title>. <source>J Res Med Sci</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>440</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1735-1995.163960</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26487872?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26487872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahmanian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Shafiee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Aminaee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dual burden of body weight among Iranian children and adolescents in 2003 and 2010: the CASPIAN-III study</article-title>. <source>Arch Med Sci</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>96</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5114/aoms.2014.40735</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24701221?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24701221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martikainen</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Marmot</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Socioeconomic differences in weight gain and determinants and consequences of coronary risk factors</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>719</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcn/69.4.719</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10197574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10197574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of community environmental factors on obesity among Korean adults: a multilevel analysis</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Health</source> (<year>2014</year>) 36:e2014036. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4178/epih/e2014036</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25666167?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25666167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baygi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorosty</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Asayesh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezapour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary predictors of childhood obesity in a representative sample of children in north east of Iran</article-title>. <source>Zhongguo Dang Dai Er Ke Za Zhi</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>501</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7499/j.issn.1008-8830.2013.07.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23866267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23866267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Payab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Qorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Motlagh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranjbar</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardalan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Association of junk food consumption with high blood pressure and obesity in Iranian children and adolescents: the CASPIAN-IV study</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>582</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jped.2014.07.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Conde</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Independent effects of income and education on the risk of obesity in the brazilian adult population</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>131</volume>:<fpage>881S</fpage>&#x02212;<lpage>6S</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/131.3.881S</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11238779?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boonpleng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Corte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mccreary</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergren</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ecological influences of early childhood obesity: a multilevel analysis</article-title>. <source>West J Nurs Res</source>. <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>742</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0193945913480275.</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23493675?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23493675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pate</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Addy</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of compliance with a new physical activity guideline for preschool-age children</article-title>. <source>Child Obes.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/chi.2014.0143</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26121562?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26121562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasnain</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradlee</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Beverage intake in early childhood and change in body fat from preschool to adolescence</article-title>. <source>Child Obes.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/chi.2013.0004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24450382?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24450382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>