<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6326548</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0209746</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-18-12046</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological Parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body Weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Body Mass Index</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological Parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body Weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Body Mass Index</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological Parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body Weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Obesity</subject><subj-group><subject>Childhood Obesity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological Parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body Weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Obesity</subject><subj-group><subject>Childhood Obesity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological Parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body Weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Obesity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological Parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body Weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Obesity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavior</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavior</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Biological Tissue</subject><subj-group><subject>Adipose Tissue</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Biological Tissue</subject><subj-group><subject>Adipose Tissue</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Nutrition</subject><subj-group><subject>Diet</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Nutrition</subject><subj-group><subject>Diet</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Public and Occupational Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Physical Activity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematical and Statistical Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Metaanalysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Metaanalysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Interventions for obesity among schoolchildren: A systematic review and meta-analyses</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Interventions on childhood obesity</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>A. Hamid</surname><given-names>Mohamad Shariff</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Project administration</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Validation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5737-7226</contrib-id><name><surname>Sazlina</surname><given-names>Shariff Ghazali</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Project administration</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Software</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Validation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>
<addr-line>Unit of Sports Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, Wilayah Persekutuan, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Family Medicine, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Universiti Putra Malaysia, Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Taheri</surname><given-names>Shahrad</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Weill Cornell Medical College in Qatar, QATAR</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>sazlina@upm.edu.my</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e0209746</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 A. Hamid, Sazlina</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>A. Hamid, Sazlina</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0209746.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec001"><title>Background</title><p>Childhood overweight and obesity has emerged as a major public health threat worldwide with challenges in its management. This review assessed the effectiveness of interventions for childhood overweight and obesity.</p></sec><sec id="sec002"><title>Methods</title><p>A systematic literature search was conducted using CINAHL, EMBASE, Ovid MEDLINE, PsycINFO and SPORTDiscus databases to retrieve articles published from 1st January 2000 to 31<sup>st</sup> December 2017. Randomised controlled trials (RCTs) and quasi-experimental studies comparing different strategies in managing overweight and obesity among schoolchildren (6 to 12 years of age) were included. The main outcomes of interest were reductions in weight related variables included anthropometry and body composition measurements. All variables were analysed using random effects meta-analyses.</p></sec><sec id="sec003"><title>Results</title><p>Fourteen studies were reviewed, 13 were RCTs and one was a quasi-experimental study. The risk of bias for randomisation was low risk for all of RCTs except for one, which was unclear. The risk of bias for randomisation was high for the quasi-experimental study. Most interventions incorporated lifestyle changes and behavioural strategies such as coping and problem solving skills with family involvement. The meta-analyses did not show significant effects of the intervention in reducing weight related outcomes when compared with controls.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Meta-analyses of the selected studies did not show significant effects of the interventions on weight related outcomes among overweight and obese schoolchildren when compared with controls. The role of interdisciplinary team approaches with family involvement using behaviour and lifestyle strategies to curb obesity among schoolchildren is important.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>We would like to thank Universiti Putra Malaysia for their support in conducting this review.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><page-count count="19"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec005"><title>Introduction</title><p>Childhood overweight and obesity is a serious public health problem worldwide in the 21<sup>st</sup> century. The prevalence of overweight and obesity has increased in almost all countries worldwide especially in economically developed countries [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>The traditional perception that a heavy child is a healthy child has changed based on evidence that overweight and obesity in childhood is associated with a wide range of serious health complications [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Overweight and obese children are more likely to have cardiovascular (e.g. hypertension, heart disease, high cholesterol), metabolic (e.g. type 2 diabetes), and psychosocial illnesses (e.g. eating disorders, depression and low self-esteem) than their normal-weight counterparts [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Also, children who were overweight and obese are at greater risk of premature illness and death in later life [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>The United Nations International Children&#x02019;s Emergency Fund (UNICEF) defined overweight and obesity as excessive and unbalanced nutrition to a point at which health is adversely affected [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The aetiology and pathogenesis of overweight and obesity often involve complex interaction between genetic makeup and environmental factors. Adoption of sedentary behaviour (physical inactivity, watching television and sitting in front of computer) combined with excess caloric consumption are examples of the environmental factors that are potentially modifiable in the battle against overweight and obesity [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>While the fundamental principles of weight management in children might seems straightforward through reduction in energy intake and increase energy expenditure, the results of current intervention studies on childhood overweight and obesity prevention are variable. A systematic review and meta-analyses on the management of obesity among children less than 18 years of age concluded that lifestyle interventions may lead to improvements in weight and cardio-metabolic outcomes [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, the evidence is limited on the optimal duration of the intervention and its long-term effectiveness. A more recent review conducted in 2015 that focused only on pre-school childhood obesity (&#x0003c;6 years of age) found multidisciplinary and intensive interventions have some evidence of efficacy in reducing body fat and fat mass [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Therefore, the objective of this review was to examine the effectiveness of interventions (including dietary, physical activity and behavioural interventions) in reducing weight related outcomes among overweight and obese children 6 to 12 years of age. It is hoped that the results from this review would provide information and guide medical practitioners and health policymakers on the management of childhood overweight and obesity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec006"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>A systematic review was conducted to explore the current approaches on managing overweight and obesity among schoolchildren. The review question was: How effective are current intervention(s) in reducing weight related outcomes including anthropometry and body composition among overweight or obese schoolchildren?&#x0201d; This review was registered with the International prospective register of systematic reviews (PROSPERO) CRD42016037918 [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero">https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero</ext-link>].</p><sec id="sec007"><title>Study selection</title><p>The study design considered in this review included randomised controlled trials (RCTs) and quasi-experimental studies. We included studies that compared strategies on the management of overweight and obesity among schoolchildren aged between 6 and 12 years of age to usual care or minimal advice. Overweight or obese were defined based on several criteria, including BMI z-scores (or standard deviation (SD) scores) [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], BMI percentile [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], BMI cut-offs based on age and gender [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and percentage of weight for height [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However, studies that classified overweight or obese using other definitions were also considered. The primary outcome of this review was a change in weight related outcomes, which included anthropometry (including weight, standard body mass index (BMI) in kg/m<sup>2</sup>, BMI percentile, BMI z-scores and standard deviation scores, percent of overweight, weight for height percentage, waist circumference) and body composition (including lean body mass, body fat and fat mass).</p><p>The secondary outcomes measured were changes in physical activity and dietary behaviour. Physical activity assessed using physical activity questionnaires, and/or activity monitors (such as accelerometer and pedometer) as well as assessment of sedentary activities were considered in this review. Studies reporting changes in dietary intake including carbohydrate and fat intake as well as caloric estimates were included. We excluded studies that focused on interventions for preschool age groups or adolescent, interventions on prevention of obesity, on drug treatment of obesity or on normal weight children.</p><p>Studies that included school-based or non-school based (home, clinic or community) interventions were reviewed. Interventions could include one or a combination of: (1) one-to-one or group counselling or advice, (2) self-directed or prescribed physical activity programmes (with or without supervisions), (3) dietary intervention or 4) behavioural strategies. Interventions delivered by one or more providers (healthcare providers, exercise professionals, or dietitians) were considered. There was no restriction on the type and content of the control group. Interventions could be compared with usual care (no active intervention), participants listed on waiting list or those who received minimal advice.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Data sources &#x00026; search strategy</title><p>Studies were electronically searched using EBSCOhost interface for Medline, CINAHL, Psychology and Behavioural Sciences Collection and SPORTDiscus, and EMBASE databases. We adhered to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The search strategy performed using the Medical Subject Heading (MeSH) terms and keywords. For children, search was done using the MeSH term child and the keywords child$ OR children. For overweight we used a combination of MeSH terms as follows: overweight OR obesity OR pediatric obesity. Diet [MeSH] OR diet, food and nutrition [MeSH] were used for diet and exercise [MeSH] OR physical activity for exercise and behavior therapy [MeSH]. For anthropometry we used body mass index [MeSH] OR body composition [MeSH] OR anthropometry [MeSH].</p><p>Peer-reviewed published articles between 1st January 2000 and 31<sup>st</sup> December 2017 were used. Published systematic reviews on the management of obesity among schoolchildren were used as the source of randomised controlled trials (RCTs). Potential eligible studies were hand searched from the reference lists of review articles and included studies. We limited the search to include studies that involved children between 6 and 12 years of age. All the titles, abstracts, and full-text of each study retrieved from the search were screened by both reviewers using a standardized form for study eligibility. In cases where there was any doubt on the paper eligibility, the issue was resolved through discussion until a consensus was reached. In view of limited resources for translation, articles that were published in the English language were considered in this review.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Data extraction</title><p>The titles and abstracts of all studies retrieved were reviewed following the criteria for study selection to decide if the full-text manuscripts were required for further evaluation. Each full-text article retrieved was evaluated systematically according to the study&#x02019;s: (1) objective (on the effectiveness of interventions), (2) characteristics of the study (study design, participants&#x02019; age, behavioural theoretical model, and sample size), (3) contents of the intervention (intervention strategies, intervention provider, length of intervention and follow-up contacts), (4) targeted outcome/s and (5) major findings.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Methodological quality assessment of individual studies</title><p>Each selected study was evaluated for its methodological quality using the Cochrane Collaboration tool for assessing the risk of bias (the Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Review of Interventions) [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. It covers: a) sequence generation b) allocation concealment c) blinding d) incomplete outcome data (e.g. dropouts and withdrawals) e) selective outcome reporting and f) other areas of bias. For each domain in the tool, the procedures undertaken for each study were described. Each study was rated as &#x02018;high&#x02019;, &#x02018;low&#x02019; or &#x02018;unclear&#x02019; risk of bias based on a judgement of the gathered information. These judgements were made independently by two review authors based on the predetermined criteria and later discussed in a meeting until a consensus achieved.</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Data synthesis and analyses</title><p>We conducted a narrative synthesis based on the primary and secondary outcomes of this review. The primary outcome measures were pooled and calculated using the statistical software RevMan 5.3, according to the Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Attempts to contact the authors to obtain the raw data for data analysis was made but to no avail. The results of the BMI z-score, waist circumference and body fat percentage were analysed using weighted or standardized mean differences as a measure of effect size, with 95% confidence intervals. Since the participant demographics and clinical settings differed among studies, we assumed the presence of heterogeneity a priori. Therefore, we used a random-effects model to pool the results. We assessed heterogeneity using the Cochran&#x02019;s Q statistic of heterogeneity with reported p-value and the degree of inconsistency across studies was quantified using I<sup>2</sup>. In studies with three arm RCTs, each of the intervention group was analysed independently and compared with the control group. A funnel plot was performed to determine the presence of potential publication bias using the statistical software RevMan 5.3.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec012"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec013"><title>Literature search</title><p>Three hundreds and two articles were identified through the five databases and cross referencing. Twenty were removed due to duplication. After screening the titles and abstracts, 69 full-text articles were retrieved and assessed for eligibility. Fifty-five articles were excluded because they did not fulfil the selection criteria. The reasons for exclusion included participants age were not between 6 and 12 years of age (n = 35), studies identified were neither RCT nor quasi (n = 13), the comparison group was with normal weight children (n = 1), intervention focused on diabetes prevention (n = 1), not an original research article (n = 2), not in English language (n = 1), and data presented was on cost-analysis (n = 1). A total of 14 articles were included in the narrative synthesis and eight were included in the meta-analyses. The flow diagram for the study selection is described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209746.g001">Fig 1</xref>.</p><fig id="pone.0209746.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0209746.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Flow diagram for selected studies.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0209746.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>Characteristics of selected studies</title><p><xref rid="pone.0209746.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarises the characteristics of the selected studies. Thirteen RCTs [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and one three-arm quasi-experimental study were reviewed [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Three RCTs were conducted in North America [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], three in Israel [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], the remaining studies were conducted in Netherlands [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], Norway [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], Finland [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], New Zealand [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], United Kingdom [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], Australia [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and Malaysia [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. As for the study setting, three studies were conducted in the community [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], five in the hospitals [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], and three in the clinics [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], of which two were in academic research clinics [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Two studies were home-based [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], and another was conducted in school [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="pone.0209746.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0209746.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of selected studies.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0209746.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0209746.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author, year, country</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants,<break/>Sample size</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention/ Control</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention length, Follow-up (FU) from baseline, Retention rate</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention provider</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcomes</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significance difference between groups</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>RCT, Hospital-based</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kalarchian et. al., 2007, USA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 8&#x02013;12 years<break/>&#x02022; Obese (BMI percentile &#x02265;97<sup>th</sup>), no comorbidities &#x00026; not on medications to affect weight<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 192<break/>(IG: 97; CG: 95)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family based intervention<break/>&#x02022; 20 weekly 60-minutes group sessions for 6 months<break/>&#x02022; 6 booster sessions (3 group sessions + 3 telephone calls) between 6 &#x00026; 12 months<break/>&#x02022; Behavioural strategies: goal setting, problem solving &#x00026; self-regulation skills<break/>&#x02022; PA: education to &#x02191; PA &#x00026; &#x02193; sedentary activities/screen time &#x0003c; 15hours/week<break/>&#x02022; Diet: Traffic light Eating Plan<break/>Control: usual care&#x02013; 2 nutrition consultation to develop individual nutrition plan (Traffic light Eating Plan)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 months<break/>FU:<break/>18 months<break/>Retention:<break/>At 12 months:<break/>IG: 75.3%<break/>CG: 69.5%<break/>At 18 months:<break/>IG: 83.5%<break/>CG: 85.3%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lifestyle coach, dietitian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary:<break/>1. Percent overweight (%OW)<break/>Secondary:<break/>1. Waist circumference<break/>2. Body fat (DEXA scan)<break/>Did not measure PA &#x00026; dietary intake<break/>Measured metabolic health outcomes:<break/>BP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, for waist circumference and body fat percentage at 12 months (no measurements done at 18 months)<break/>No, for %OW at 12 and 18 months</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Golley et. el., 2007, Australia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 6&#x02013;9 years<break/>&#x02022; Obese (BMI z-&#x02264;3.5), no comorbidities &#x00026; not on medications to affect weight<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 111 (3-arm RCT)<break/>(IGP: 37; IGP+DA: 38; CG: 36)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IGP: Intensive lifestyle education<break/>&#x02022; Based on Positive Parenting Program (Triple P) to promote child&#x02019;s behavior on dietary + activity<break/>&#x02022; 4 weekly 2-hour group sessions<break/>&#x02022; 15&#x02013;20 minutes of 4 weekly then 3 monthly individual telephone sessions<break/>IGP+DA:<break/>&#x02022; Parent: Triple P + 7 intensive lifestyle support group sessions (family focused healthy eating)<break/>&#x02022; Child: structured supervised aerobic activities (details not stated)<break/>Control: wait-listed; received general &#x0201c;Healthy Lifestyle&#x0201d; pamphlet + 3&#x02013;4 5-minutes telephone call (retention strategy)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months<break/>FU:<break/>12 months<break/>Retention:<break/>At 12 months:<break/>IGP: 78.4%<break/>IGP+DA: 81.6%<break/>CG: 86.1%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietitian, PA experts</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary:<break/>1. BMI z-scores<break/>Secondary:<break/>1. Waist circumference<break/>Did not measure PA &#x00026; dietary intake<break/>Measured metabolic health outcomes:<break/>BP, glucose, Lipids profile<break/>No measurements for CG at 6 months for comparison</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No, for BMI z-score &#x00026; waist circumference at 12 months</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>RCT, Hospital-based</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">di Niet et. al., 2012, Netherlands</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 7&#x02013;12 years<break/>&#x02022; Overweight (BMI SDS &#x0003e;1.1) or obese (BMI SDS &#x0003e;2.3)<break/>&#x02022; no comorbidities<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 114<break/>(IG: 73; CG: 68)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-monitoring of lifestyle behaviour via a short message service maintenance treatment (SMSMT) using mobile phones with personalized feedback<break/>&#x02022; 8 group sessions in 3 months<break/>&#x02022; Behavioural strategies: coping skills, goal setting, problem solving &#x00026; self-regulation skills<break/>&#x02022; PA: exercise behavior&#x02013;content was not stated<break/>&#x02022; Diet: healthy eating&#x02013;content was not stated<break/>Control: Same content as IG but no SMSMT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months<break/>FU:<break/>12 months<break/>Retention:<break/>Measured at 12 months only:<break/>IG: 86.3%<break/>CG: 69.1%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychologist, dietitian, paediatrician &#x00026; physiotherapist</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary:<break/>1. BMI SDS (z-scores)<break/>Secondary:<break/>1. Eating behavior (Dutch Eating behavior questionnaire)<break/>Did not measure PA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None for BMI SD scores or eating behavior</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hystad et. al. 2013, Norway</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 7&#x02013;12 years<break/>&#x02022; Obese (BMI z-scores &#x02265;2)<break/>&#x02022; No comorbidities<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 99<break/>(IG: 47; CG: 52)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapist-led group (TLG) to enhance parental competence to accomplish targeted lifestyle changes<break/>&#x02022; 10 group sessions + 5 individual sessions on diet and PA<break/>&#x02022; Written manual<break/>&#x02022; Physical activity: at least 1 hour/day of moderate intensity &#x00026; max. 2 hour/day sedentary behavior<break/>&#x02022; Diet: Healthy eating<break/>Control: Self-help group (principle of mutual help, derived from the participants&#x02019; own experiences and knowledge. No education or guidance to improve weight</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months<break/>FU:<break/>24 months<break/>Retention:<break/>At 6 months:<break/>IG: 89.3%<break/>CG: 90.4%<break/>At 24 months:<break/>IG: 76.6%<break/>CG: 84.6%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychologists, dietitians, paediatricians &#x00026; physiotherapists</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary:<break/>1. Body fat (DEXA scan)<break/>2. BMI z-scores<break/>3. Dietary intake (4-day food record: Norwegian Food composition table)<break/>Did not measure PA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None for body fat, BMI z-score and diet</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>RCT, Clinic-based</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estabrooks et. al., 2009, USA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 8&#x02013;12 years<break/>&#x02022; Overweight or obese (BMI percentile &#x02265;85<sup>th</sup>)<break/>&#x02022; Did not state about comorbidities<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 220 (3-arm RCT)<break/>(IGFC: 50; IGGroup: 85; IGIVR:85)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family connection (FC) Interventions<break/>&#x02022; FC-workbook: self-help connection 61-pages workbook for parents &#x00026; served as control group<break/>&#x02022; FC group: workbook + 2-hours x 2 weekly group sessions with dietitian<break/>&#x02022; FC interactive voice response (IVR) counselling: workbook+ group sessions +10 automated IVR tailored counselling sessions over 20 weeks<break/>&#x02022; Behavioural strategies: goal setting, problem solving &#x00026; role modelling<break/>&#x02022; PA: education to &#x02191; PA &#x00026; &#x02193; sedentary activities/TV viewing<break/>&#x02022; Diet: education on healthy eating</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months<break/>FU:12 months<break/>Retention:<break/>At 6 months<break/>IGFC:76%<break/>IGGroup:75%<break/>IGIVR: 80%<break/>At 12 months:<break/>IGFC:72%<break/>IGGroup:66%<break/>IGIVR: 74%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietitian (for IGGroup &#x00026; IGIVR) &#x00026; research team</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary:<break/>1. BMI z-score<break/>Secondary:<break/>1. Dietary intake (Block Kids Questionnaire)<break/>2. PA (Youth Behavior Risk Survey)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, for BMI z-score<break/>Reduced in IGIVR compared to IG FC or IGGroup at 6 &#x00026; 12 months<break/>No, for PA and dietary intake over time</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>RCT, Research clinic-based</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wafa et. al., 2011, Malaysia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 7&#x02013;11 years<break/>&#x02022; Obese (BMI percentile &#x0003e;95<sup>th</sup>), no comorbidities<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 107<break/>(IG: 52; CG: 55)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adapted program from Scottish Childhood Obesity Treatment Trial<break/>&#x02022; Parent: 8 8-hour group sessions over 26 weeks with dietitian + 1 session with clinical psychologist for behavioural strategies (self-monitoring, goal setting, problem solving &#x00026; relapse prevention)<break/>&#x02022; PA education (&#x02191; PA &#x00026; &#x02193; sedentary activities/TV viewing)<break/>&#x02022; Diet: education on Traffic light eating plans)<break/>&#x02022; Child: PA sessions (details not provided)<break/>Control: delayed treatment after 6 months</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months<break/>FU: none<break/>Retention:<break/>IG: 65%<break/>CG: 84%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietitian, clinical psychologist. Exercise instructor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary:<break/>1. BMI z-score<break/>2. BMI<break/>Secondary:<break/>1. PA (accelerometer)<break/>Dietary intake not measured</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No, for BMI z-score &#x00026; PA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boutelle et. al., 2013, USA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 8&#x02013;12 years<break/>&#x02022; Overweight or obese (BMI percentile 85<sup>th</sup> to 98<sup>th</sup>), no comorbidities<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 50<break/>(IG: 25; CG: 25)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guided self-help pediatric obesity (GSH-PO)<break/>&#x02022; Behavioural program with12 individual sessions over 5 months (alternate week visits for 20 minutes each),<break/>&#x02022; Written manual for child &#x00026; parent and activities manual &#x00026; self-monitoring booklets<break/>&#x02022; Behavioural strategies (stimulus control, motivation, cognitive skils, social support &#x00026; relapse prevention)<break/>&#x02022; PA education (&#x02191; PA &#x00026; &#x02193; sedentary activities)<break/>&#x02022; Diet: education on Traffic light eating plans)<break/>Control: delayed treatment after 5 months</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 months<break/>FU: 11 months<break/>Retention:<break/>IG: 92% at 5 months; no loss to FU at 11 months<break/>CG: 100%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Graduate student in clinical psychology</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary:<break/>1. BMI<break/>2. BMI z-score<break/>3. % OW<break/>Secondary:<break/>1. Dietary intake (3 days 24-hour diet recall)<break/>2. PA (accelerometer)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, for BMI, BMI z-score &#x00026; %OW at 5 months<break/>Yes, for BMI z-score &#x00026; %OW at 11 months for IG but no control group<break/>No for PA and dietary intake over time</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>RCT, School based</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kalavainen et. al., 2007, Finland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 7&#x02013;9 years<break/>&#x02022; Obese (weight for height of 120 to 200%)<break/>&#x02022; No comorbidities<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 70<break/>(IG: 35; CG: 35)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family-centred group program focus on behavioural &#x00026; solution-oriented therapy<break/>&#x02022; 15 group sessions of 90 minutes<break/>&#x02022; Written manual<break/>&#x02022; Behavioural strategies: cognitive behavioural therapy workbook (Magnificent Kids)<break/>&#x02022; PA: education on &#x02191; PA &#x00026; &#x02193; sedentary activities<break/>&#x02022; Diet: education on healthy diet &#x00026; meal pattern<break/>Control: Routine counseling (booklet on weight management, eating habits &#x00026; PA + 2 individual sessions with school nurse)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months<break/>FU: 12 months<break/>Retention:<break/>IG &#x00026; CG: 97.1% at 6 months, no loss to FU at 12 months</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietitian, school nurses</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary:<break/>1. Weight for height<break/>Secondary:<break/>1. BMI<break/>2. BMI SD scores (z-scores)<break/>PA or dietary intake were not measured as an outcome</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, for weight for height, BMI &#x00026; BMI-SDS at 6 months<break/>Yes, for weight for height &#x00026; BMI at 12 months</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>RCT, Home-based</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goldfield et al., 2006, Canada</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 8&#x02013;12 years<break/>&#x02022; Overweight (BMI percentile 85<sup>th</sup> to 94<sup>th</sup>) or obese (BMI percentile &#x0003e;94<sup>th</sup>)<break/>&#x02022; Watching TV (VCR/DVD or video games) &#x0003e;15 hours<break/>&#x02022; &#x0003c;30 minutes physical activities<break/>&#x02022; No condition that limits PA<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 30<break/>(IG: 14; CG: 16)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Open-loop feedback (requires person to do PA, accelerometer measure PA objectively, which provide feedback. Child will be rewarded access to television when perform PA) + reinforcement by a parent<break/>&#x02022; Bi weekly meeting with research team to determine the amount of television time based on the accelerometer<break/>&#x02022; PA accumulated will be rewarded with access to television<break/>&#x02022; Diet: None<break/>Control: Open-loop feedback only</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 weeks<break/>FU: none<break/>Retention:<break/>100% both groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary:<break/>1. BMI<break/>Secondary:<break/>1. PA (accelerometer)<break/>2. PA (Past Day PA Recall + television viewing time)<break/>3. Dietary intake (3 days 24-hour diet recall)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, for BMI, PA, television viewing time, fat intake, calories from snacks &#x00026;snack intake during television watching</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maddison et al., 2014, New Zealand</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 9&#x02013;12 years<break/>&#x02022; Used electronic media (&#x02265;15 hours per week,)<break/>&#x02022; Overweight or obese (as per Cole International cut-points)<break/>&#x02022; No condition that limits PA<break/>Parent/primary caregiver participation<break/>Sample size: 251<break/>(IG: 127; CG:124)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screen-Time Weight-loss Intervention Targeting Children at Home(SWITCH)<break/>&#x02022; One face-to-face individual education and support for primary caregivers to reduce media use at home.<break/>&#x02022; Monthly e-newsletter on reduced screen-based activity &#x00026; links to community-based programs<break/>&#x02022; Behavioural strategies: self-monitoring, role modelling<break/>&#x02022; PA: focus on sedentary behavior<break/>&#x02022; Diet: none<break/>Control: usual care</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 weeks<break/>FU: None<break/>Retention:<break/>IG: 95%<break/>CG: 94%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary caregivers</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary:<break/>1. BMI z-scores<break/>Secondary:<break/>1. BMI<break/>2. Waist circumference<break/>3. Body fat (BIA)<break/>4. PA (7-day physical activity questionnaire + sedentary activity)<break/>5. Dietary intake (Food frequency questionnaire)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None for BMI z-scores, BMI, waist circumference, body fat, PA (including sedentary time) and dietary intake</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>RCT, Community-based</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nemet et al., 2008, Israel</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 8&#x02013;11 years<break/>&#x02022; Obese (BMI percentile &#x0003e;95<sup>th</sup>)<break/>&#x02022; No comorbidities<break/>&#x02022; Not on medications that interfere with growth or weight control<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 22<break/>(IG: 11; CG:11)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; PA: 2x a week of 1-hour training group session + 1x/week movement therapy group session at Sport Centre + 30&#x02013;45 minutes home-based walking/weight bearing exercise 2x/week + reduce sedentary behaviour<break/>&#x02022; Diet: 14 sessions with dietitian on food pyramid with written dietary information &#x00026; received balanced hypocaloric diet<break/>Control: 1 x nutritional consultation &#x00026; instructed to perform physical activity three times per week on their own</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months<break/>FU: None<break/>Retention:<break/>100% for both groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietitian, sports trainers, movement therapists</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Did not specify which outcomes as primary or secondary outcomes<break/>1. BMI percentile<break/>2. BMI<break/>3. Body fat (BIA)<break/>4. Screen time<break/>5. Diet (2 day 48-hour diet recall)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, for BMI percentiles &#x00026; screen time</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nemet et al., 2013, Israel</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 7&#x02013;9 years<break/>&#x02022; Obese<break/>&#x02022; (BMI percentile &#x0003e;98<sup>th</sup>)<break/>&#x02022; No comorbidities<break/>&#x02022; Not on medication causing obesity<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 45<break/>(IG: 25; CG: 20)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; PA: 2x a week of 1-hour training group session + 1x/week movement therapy group session at Sport Centre + 30&#x02013;45 minutes home-based walking/weight bearing exercise 2x/week + reduce sedentary behavior<break/>&#x02022; Diet: 14 sessions with dietitian on food pyramid with written dietary information &#x00026; received balanced hypocaloric diet<break/>Control: one nutritional consultation and instructed to perform physical activity daily</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months<break/>FU: None<break/>Retention:<break/>IG: 88%<break/>CG: 90%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietitian, sports trainers, movement therapists</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Did not specify the primary or secondary outcomes<break/>1. Weight<break/>2. BMI percentile<break/>3. BMI<break/>4. Skinfolds (triceps &#x00026; subscapular)<break/>5. Body fat (BIA)<break/>6. Physical activity pattern (METS)<break/>7. Screen time</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, for weight, BMI, BMI percentile, skinfolds &#x00026; PA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sacher et al., 2010, UK</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 8&#x02013;12 years<break/>&#x02022; Obese (BMI percentile &#x02265; 98<sup>th</sup>)<break/>&#x02022; No comorbidities<break/>Parent participation<break/>Sample size: 116 (IG: 60; CG:56)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mind, Exercise, Nutrition, Do it (MEND) program<break/>&#x02022; Group based sessions for 9 weeks at community venues<break/>&#x02022; 12-weeks of free family swim pass<break/>&#x02022; Behavioural strategies: 8 sessions in 9 weeks on stimulus control, goal setting, reinforcement, response prevention<break/>&#x02022; PA: 18 group exercise sessions for 1 hour, over 9 weeks<break/>&#x02022; Diet: 8 group nutrition education sessions on healthy eating with written instructions<break/>Control: Wait-list</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months<break/>FU:<break/>12 months<break/>Retention:<break/>IG: 61.7%<break/>CG: 80.3%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietitians, Health trainers</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Did not specify the primary or secondary outcomes<break/>1. Weight<break/>2. Waist circumference<break/>3. Lean body mass (BIA)<break/>4. Fat mass (BIA)<break/>5. Body fat (BIA)<break/>6. BMI z-score<break/>7. BMI<break/>8. Physical activity (hour/week) (non-validated questionnaire + sedentary activity)<break/>Measured metabolic health outcomes:<break/>BP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, for waist circumference, BMI z-score, BMI &#x00026; sedentary activity at 6 months<break/>Yes, for waist circumference, BMI z-scores &#x00026; PA at 12 months but no comparison control group</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>Quasi-experimental, Hospital-based</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shalitin et. al. 2009, Israel</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02022; Age: 6&#x02013;11 years<break/>&#x02022; Obese (BMI percentile &#x0003e;95<sup>th</sup>)<break/>&#x02022; No comorbidities<break/>&#x02022; Not using medication that might interfere with weight control<break/>Sample size: 162 (IGEx = 52, IGDiet = 55, IGDietEx = 55)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IGEx: Exercise intervention (3-day weekly, 90 minutes per training group session) directed by 3 professional coaches<break/>IGDiet: Diet education with 12 weekly of 60 minutes group sessions with a dietician with written information on food pyramid and healthy eating. Also prescribed on balanced hypocaloric diet<break/>IGDietEx: Combination of both interventions</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 weeks<break/>FU:<break/>52 weeks<break/>Retention:<break/>IGEx: 42.3%<break/>IGDiet: 49.1% IGDietEx: 50.9%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exercise professional coaches, dietitians</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Did not specify the primary or secondary outcomes<break/>1. Waist circumference<break/>2. Body fat (BIA)<break/>3. BMI SDS (z scores)<break/>4. BMI<break/>PA and dietary intake were not measured as an outcome</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, for BMI SDS (GDiet and IGDietEx compared to IGEx at 12 and 52 weeks)<break/>None between IGDiet and IGDietEx over time</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>NOTE: RCT = randomised controlled trial, BMI = body mass index, SDS = Standard deviation scores, IG = intervention group, CG = control group, PA = physical activity, SD = standard deviation, BP = blood pressure, DEXA = Dual-Energy X-Ray Absorptiometry, BIA = Bio-impedance analysis</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Five studies recruited children who were overweight or obese [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], while nine recruited only obese children [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. All studies except one excluded participants with comorbidities [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Most studies used BMI percentile to classify overweight or obese [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Three studies used BMI z-scores [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], one used weight for height percentage [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and one used the International Obesity Task Force cut points [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] to classify overweight or obese. Interestingly, the definition used to classify overweight and obese differs in the included studies despite using the same measures. For example, some studies defined obese as BMI percentile &#x0003e;94<sup>th</sup> centile [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] while others as BMI percentile &#x0003e;98<sup>th</sup> centile [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p>All studies had interventions that integrated interdisciplinary approaches involving parent or family. Selected studies incorporated either a combination of behavioural strategies, physical activity, and dietary component [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], behavioural strategies and physical activity [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] or physical activity and dietary component without behavioural strategies [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. All interventions were delivered by a group of healthcare providers (psychologist, dietitian/nutritionist, physical/sport therapist) except in one study where the intervention was delivered by a clinical psychology graduate student [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. One study used short message services [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], while another used an automated interactive voice response system [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] to maintain behavioural change. Only five studies incorporated health behavioural theories in their interventions, namely social learning and cognitive theory [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] alone or combined with behavioural theories or models [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], social ecological theory [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] or the trans-theoretical model [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The duration of intervention varied between 8 weeks and 12 months. In nine studies participants and their families were followed up for 12 to 24 months [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Six RCTs were compared with usual care or wait-listed groups [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] while the others were compared with groups that received minimal advice.</p><p>All studies assessed weight related measurements as their primary outcomes. Seven studies used BMI z-scores [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and two studies included standard BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>) [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] as their primary outcomes. Other studies also included body fat [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], percentage of overweight [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and weight for height percentage [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] as their primary outcomes. Six studies measured body composition such as body fat, fat mass and lean body mass as their outcomes [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Five studies measured waist circumference as their outcome [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. One study measured skinfold thickness as their outcome [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. However, 11 studies presented more than one weight related outcomes as their outcome measures [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p>Eight studies measured changes in physical activity and sedentary behaviour including screen time [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In three studies, the level of physical activity was measured using the accelerometers [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Seven studies measured changes in dietary intake including consumptions of unhealthy snacks as outcomes [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Study quality</title><p>The risk of bias for randomisation was unclear and low for all 13 RCTs [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The risk of bias for randomisation among quasi-experimental studies was high as expected. The quasi-experimental study stated random assignment of participants in their interventions. However, details on the randomisation technique was not elaborated [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].The allocation concealment was described in six (43%) studies [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Blinding of participant and personnel was lacking in all studies as anticipated because of the nature of the interventions. In addressing detection bias, blinding of outcome assessment was unclear in most studies. In three studies the outcome measures were performed by assessors blinded to participants&#x02019; grouping [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The risk for incomplete outcome data was low for all studies except for one [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Sacher et. al (2010) declared loss to follow-up among their participants but did not apply intention to treat analysis [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The proportion of studies with low, unclear and high risk of bias is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209746.g002">Fig 2</xref>.</p><fig id="pone.0209746.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0209746.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Quality assessment of selected studies.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0209746.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec016"><title>Effect of interventions compared with controls</title><p>Five studies that incorporated behavioural strategies with exercise and dietary interventions reported positive effects on the weight related outcomes [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Other studies that included behavioural skills and exercise alone [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] or combination of exercise and dietary interventions [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] also reported positive effects on the weight related outcomes. Of the seven RCTs that measured BMI z-score, four showed significant reductions among participants in the intervention compared to controls [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Three of these studies showed reductions at 6-months follow up [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], of which two studies delivered their interventions in groups sessions [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Two studies that incorporated family group sessions of behavioural strategies with exercise and dietary interventions showed no reductions in the BMI z-scores when compared to control groups [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. One of these RCTs used SMS to encourage self-monitoring and provided personalised feedback [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Two RCTs that measured BMI percentile also showed reductions at post-intervention when compared to their controls [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Both studies incorporated group-based diet and physical activity programs with family engagement. The quasi experimental study found dietary intervention alone or combined with physical activities leads to significant reductions in BMI z-scores compared to exercise intervention alone [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p>Four out of eight RCTs showed increased physical activity in the intervention group compared to the control [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. One study also showed reduction in sedentary activity among participants in the intervention group. The change was sustained at 6-months follow-up [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Seven RCTs measured dietary intake behaviour as their outcomes, which included carbohydrate and fat intake as well as estimation of caloric intake [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Only two studies showed significant reductions in dietary or caloric intake when compared to the control groups at post-intervention, however, they did not follow up the participants [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. One study showed reductions in fat and caloric intake from snacks and reduction in snack intake during watching television [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>All community-based intervention studies reported positive effects on changes of BMI z-score, BMI percentile, waist circumference and/or skinfolds, as well as improvement in sedentary behaviours [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. However, only one study followed participants up to 12 months and showed sustained effects on these outcomes [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. One of the three hospital-based studies [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], one of the two home-based [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and each of the clinic-based [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and school-based [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] interventions reported positive effects on the outcomes.</p><p>We performed meta-analyses to determine the effect of interventions on changes in BMI z-score, waist circumference and body fat percentage based on different intervention strategies. Some of the selected studies varied in their primary outcomes, therefore, data from studies with similar outcomes were pooled and analysed. Data from eight RCTs (n = 969 participants) were pooled to determine the effects of intervention strategies on the changes of BMI z-scores. However, two of the studies were 3-arm RCTs, which we analysed each intervention separately. No statistically significant difference was found between intervention and controls (standardised mean difference = - 0.14; 95% CI = - 0.87, 0.60; p = 0.72) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209746.g003">Fig 3</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. A meta-analyses on three RCTs (n = 434 participants) did not show significant positive effects of any intervention strategies on the changes of waist circumference compared to controls (standardised mean difference = -0.25; 95% CI = -0.51, 0.01; p = 0.06) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209746.g004">Fig 4</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Five RCTs (n = 463 participants) pooled data showed no significant difference in the changes of body fat percentage between intervention and control (standardised mean difference = 0.30; 95% CI = - 0.17, 0.76; p = 0.21) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209746.g005">Fig 5</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0209746.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0209746.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Forest plot on BMI z-score based on intervention strategies at postintervention.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0209746.g003"/></fig><fig id="pone.0209746.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0209746.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Forest plot on BMI percentile based on intervention strategies at postintervention.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0209746.g004"/></fig><fig id="pone.0209746.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0209746.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Forest plot on body fat percentage based on intervention strategies at postintervention.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0209746.g005"/></fig><p>We only present a funnel plot for the BMI z-score outcome but not for the BMI percentile and body fat percentage. This is because a funnel plot with fewer than 10 studies in a meta-analysis would lead to low power of analysis to distinguish the chance from real asymmetry [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209746.g006">Fig 6</xref> depicts the funnel plot for the meta-analysis on the effects of the intervention on the changes in BMI z-score of the selected studies in our review. There was an asymmetry of the plot to suggest presence of publication bias.</p><fig id="pone.0209746.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0209746.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>Funnel plot on BMI z-score based on intervention strategies at postintervention.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0209746.g006"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec017"><title>Discussion</title><p>We conducted this review to evaluate the effectiveness of interventions on weight related outcomes (BMI z-score, BMI percentile and body fat percentage) and lifestyle outcomes (physical and sedentary activities, and dietary behaviour) among overweight or obese schoolchildren.</p><p>Our narrative synthesis found studies that incorporated behavioural lifestyle interventions reported positive effects on weight related outcomes. Previous reviews and meta-analyses reported interventions that incorporate lifestyle modifications including dietary restriction, physical activities (exercise) alone or in combination leads to larger effects on BMI, BMI z-scores and body composition, as well as reduced unhealthy dietary intake when compared to controls [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Moreover, a previous systematic review found addition of pharmacological intervention to behavioural lifestyle intervention led to only small effects on BMI and BMI z-score. [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Hence, this emphasised that behavioural lifestyle modification is utmost important in the management of obesity in children.</p><p>Studies that integrated behavioural skills into the lifestyle modifications intervention showed positive effects on the reductions of BMI z-scores, BMI percentile, waist circumference and body fat, as well as improved physical, sedentary and dietary behaviours. The parents of children in the trials were taught coping and problem-solving skills, which could have facilitated the weight reduction, hence, improved outcomes. A previous case control study that examined family functioning, expressed emotion and coping skills found mothers&#x02019; negative expressed emotion and coping skills were related to the child being overweight [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Hence, such behavioural skills should be incorporated as strategies in the management of obesity in children.</p><p>In this review, all studies that engaged family members in their intervention showed positive effects on weight related outcomes. Such findings are consistent with previous reviews which reported family based interventions with parental involvement led to reductions in BMI, BMI z-scores and body composition [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The engagement of parents in these trials facilitated their children in choosing healthier behaviour in addition to acting as role models for their children.</p><p>In most studies with positive effects, the delivery of the intervention involved interdisciplinary approaches involving various healthcare practitioners including dietitians, psychologists and physical or sports therapists. Moreover, in some of these studies, intervention sessions were conducted in groups. A previous systematic review on childhood obesity showed that behavioural lifestyle interventions delivered by trained specialised interventionists were effective for obesity [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Continuous external support from other people, or professionals may be important in achieving and maintaining goals.</p><p>Our review found that the studies were set in various settings, including in the community, school, home and the hospital. All community-based interventions reported positive effects on the primary outcomes. Our findings are consistent with previous systematic reviews which reported positive outcomes from combined lifestyle interventions (diet and physical activity) delivered in the community [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It was anticipated that community-based interventions would be more cost-effective compared to clinic or hospital settings. An economic evaluation on 10 RCTs reported lifestyle interventions are potentially cost-effective for obese children between 10 and 11 years of age. Its impact on health benefits and cost-savings however, would only be evident in their 6<sup>th</sup> or 7<sup>th</sup> decade of life [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p><p>The outcome measured in majority of the studies varied. Various reference datasets for weight related outcomes were used, which led to different definitions of obesity in children. The BMI z-score was often used as an outcome measure in children, however, its role in childhood obesity has been challenged. In children aged less than 9 years, BMI z-score is a weak to moderate predictor of total fat mass and body fat percentage [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In addition, it is also a weak predictor of total body fat changes over time with poor specificity [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Hence, in clinical practice, changes in body composition among obese children should not solely be monitored using BMI z-score.</p><p>Our meta-analyses showed the effects of interventions on BMI z-score, waist circumference and body fat measurements were inconclusive for the management of childhood obesity. We are not able to make comparison with a previous review [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] as they pooled standard BMI data rather than BMI z-score, waist circumference or body fat. Further their review also included adolescents. The inconclusive findings from our meta-analyses could be due to differences in intervention strategies.</p><p>Our review provides insight into the impact of lifestyle interventions combined with behavioural strategies in reducing the weight related outcomes among overweight and obese schoolchildren. The involvement of family members in the treatment of overweight and obesity could not be overemphasised. The intervention one chooses would depend on the resources in the school and the community. Using dedicated personnel to deliver the intervention was effective, but the cost and human resources demand would be high. In addition, strategies attempting to reduce unhealthy behaviours such as reducing sedentary behaviours and adopting healthy dietary intake seem to be more effective. Parents could be trained and empowered to promote the lifestyle changes required for the management of obesity in children [<xref rid="pone.0209746.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p><p>This review included both randomized and non-randomized controlled trials to provide more comprehensive views of various interventions aimed to reduce weight related outcomes. We also evaluated the effects of intervention on waist circumference and body fat percentage not just on BMI measures as these parameters are commonly monitored in clinical practice. Several limitations need to be mentioned in this review. Even though we have employed an extensive search strategy, we limited the publications to English language only, due to limited resources. Hence, the effectiveness of the interventions could be overrepresented. Our review only included RCTs and quasi-experimental studies, and not cohort studies. The latter study design would provide a better reflection of clinical practice. Our search strategy was specific for diet, nutrition and physical activity interventions. Hence, publications that used term such as weight management were not captured. Most studies included in this review had high or unclear risk of bias with regards to the allocation concealment and blinding of the assessors. Therefore, the findings reported should be interpreted with caution. Most studies also had high or unclear risk of bias for blinding of participants and personnel. However, these were unavoidable in view of the nature of the intervention. In addition, unpublished studies were not identified, thus, publication bias is possible. The funnel plot showed presence of possible publication bias which could be attributed to studies with small sample size and possibly with negative results were not published. Cost-effectiveness of interventions were not included in this review, which is an important aspect to consider when choosing an intervention. Hence, it should be considered in future reviews.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec018"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our meta-analyses showed that current interventions for the management of obesity among schoolchildren on weight related outcomes were inconclusive. However, based on the narrative synthesis, the role for behavioural lifestyle interventions with interdisciplinary team approaches and family involvement is crucial to curb obesity among schoolchildren. But more robust studies are needed to determine its effectiveness.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec019"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0209746.s001"><label>S1 File</label><caption><title>PRISMA checklist.</title><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0209746.s001.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0209746.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lobstein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jackson-Leach</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Planning for the worst: estimates of obesity and comorbidities in school-age children in 2025</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Obes</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ijpo.12185</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27684716?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27684716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Onis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bl&#x000f6;ssner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borghi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Global prevalence and trends of overweight and obesity among preschool children</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/ajcn.2010.29786</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20861173?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20861173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fryar</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flegal</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prevalence of obesity among adults and youth: United States, 2011&#x02013;2014</article-title>. <source>NCHS Data Brief</source>. <year>2015</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Overweight children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>NEJM</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>352</volume>:<fpage>2100</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMcp043052</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15901863?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15901863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Malepati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sherry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Health plans&#x02019; role in preventing overweight in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Health Affairs</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>430</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>440</lpage> 11p. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.26.2.430</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17339670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17339670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>ASEAN/UNICEF/WHO</collab>. <chapter-title>Regional report on nutrition security in ASEAN</chapter-title>, Volume <volume>2</volume>
<publisher-loc>Bangkok</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>UNICEF</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year> Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://asean.org/?static_post=regional-report-nutrition-security-asean-volume-2">http://asean.org/?static_post=regional-report-nutrition-security-asean-volume-2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Taber</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chriqui</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perna</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaloupka</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Association between state physical education (PE) requirements and PE participation, physical activity, and body mass index change</article-title>. <source>Prev Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>629</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2013.08.018</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23978523?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23978523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ros&#x000e1;rio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Padr&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The impact of an intervention taught by trained teachers on childhood overweight</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph9041355</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22690198?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22690198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garnett</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baur</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burrows</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neve</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Effectiveness of lifestyle interventions in child obesity: Systematic review with meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>130</volume>:<fpage>e1647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2012-1176</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23166346?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23166346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farragher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sosa</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>. <article-title>Treatment interventions for early childhood obesity: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Acad Pediatr</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.acap.2015.04.037</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26142067?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26142067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. WHO | BMI-for-age (5&#x02013;19 years). WHO. 2017 [cited 2018 Sep 7]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/growthref/who2007_bmi_for_age/en/">http://www.who.int/growthref/who2007_bmi_for_age/en/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Defining childhood obesity. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/obesity/childhood/defining.htmlCe">https://www.cdc.gov/obesity/childhood/defining.htmlCe</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lobstein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Extended International (IOTF) body mass index cut-offs for thinness, overweight and obesity</article-title>. <source>Pediatric Obesity</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>284</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2047-6310.2012.00064.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22715120?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22715120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Poustie</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watling</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashby</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reliability of percentage ideal weight for height</article-title>. <source>Arch Disease Childhood</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10906035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <collab>The PRISMA Group</collab>. <article-title>Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses: The PRISMA statement</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e1000097</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000097</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19621072?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19621072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Higgins JPT, Green. Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions Version 5.1.0. The Cochrane Collaboration; 2011.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boutelle</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rock</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crow</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Guided self-help for the treatment of pediatric obesity</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>e1435</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1442</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2012-2204</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23545372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23545372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Niet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van den Akker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buijks</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Klerk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The effect of a short message service maintenance treatment on body mass index and psychological well-being in overweight and obese children: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Obes</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2047-6310.2012.00048.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22492669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22492669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kalarchian</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arslanian</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Houck</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Family-based treatment of severe pediatric obesity: Randomized controlled Trial</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>1060</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2008-3727</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19786444?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19786444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Golley</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Magarey</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baur</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinbeck</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Twelve-month effectiveness of a parent-led, family-focused weight-management program for prepubertal children: A randomized, controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2006-1746</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17332205?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17332205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kalavainen</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Korppi</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nuutinen</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Clinical efficacy of group-based treatment for childhood obesity compared with routinely given individual counseling</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1500</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goldfield</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mallory</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Legg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lumb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Effects of open-loop feedback on physical activity and television viewing in overweight and obese children: a randomized, controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>e157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage> 1p. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2005-3052</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16818530?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16818530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olds</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dewes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Screen-Time Weight-loss Intervention Targeting Children at Home (SWITCH): A randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12966-014-0111-2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25204320?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25204320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wafa</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Talib</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamzaid</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McColl</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rajikan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Randomized controlled trial of a good practice approach to treatment of childhood obesity in Malaysia: Malaysian Childhood Obesity Treatment Trial (MASCOT)</article-title>. <source>Int J Pediatr Obesity</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e62</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Estabrooks</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shoup</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gattshall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dandamudi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shetterly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Automated telephone counseling for parents of overweight children: A randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42.e2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2008.09.024</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19095163?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19095163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hystad</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinsbekk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Odegard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wichstrom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gudbrandsen</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name>. <article-title>A randomised study on the effectiveness of therapist-led v. self-help parental intervention for treating childhood obesity</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>1143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114513000056</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23388524?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23388524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nemet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ben-Haim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pantanowits</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eliakim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of a combined intervention for treating severely obese prepubertal children</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jpem-2012-0225</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23382300?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23382300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nemet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barzilay-Teeni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eliakim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Treatment of childhood obesity in obese families</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>461</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 18655528?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18655528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sacher</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kolotourou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chadwick</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Randomized controlled trial of the MEND program: a family-based community intervention for childhood obesity</article-title>. <source>Obesity</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>S62</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/oby.2009.433</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20107463?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20107463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shalitin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashkenazi-Hoffnung</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yackobovitch-Gavan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagelberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karni</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hershkovitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Effects of a twelve-week randomized intervention of exercise and/or diet on weight loss and weight maintenance, and other metabolic parameters in obese preadolescent children</article-title>. <source>HRP</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sterne</surname><given-names>JAC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>JPA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terrin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Recommendations for examining and interpreting funnel plot asymmetry in meta-analyses of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2011</year>:<volume>342</volume>:<fpage>d4002</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Coppock</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ridolfi</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>St Paul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilfley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Current approaches to the management of pediatric overweight and obesity</article-title>. <source>Curr Treat Options Cardiovasc Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>343</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11936-014-0343-0</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25205083?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25205083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peirson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fitzpatrick-Lewis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Usman Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raina</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Treatment of overweight and obesity in children and youth: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>CMAJ Open</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>E35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9778/cmajo.20140047</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25844368?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25844368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sepulveda</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lacruz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Real</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin-Peinador</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Examining maternal psychopathology, family functioning and coping skills in childhood obesity: A case-control study</article-title>. <source>Eur Eat Disord Rev</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/erv.2527</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28568706?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28568706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kelishadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Azizi-Soleiman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Controlling childhood obesity: A systematic review on strategies and challenges</article-title>. <source>J Res Med Sci</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>993</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1008</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 25538786?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25538786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Staniford</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Breckon</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Treatment of childhood obesity: A systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Child Fam Stud</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hollingworth</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawlor</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kipping</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Economic evaluation of lifestyle interventions to treat overweight or obesity in children</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Obesity</source>. <year>2012</year>;<fpage>559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vanderwall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Randall Clark</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eickhoff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carrel</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>. <article-title>BMI is a poor predictor of adiposity in young overweight and obese children</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatrics</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12887-017-0891-z</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28577356?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28577356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Flegal</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Childhood obesity: Are we all speaking the same language?</article-title>
<source>Adv Nutr</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>159S</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>166S</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/an.111.000307</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22332047?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22332047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vanderwall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eickhoff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Randall Clark</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carrel</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>. <article-title>BMI z-score in obese children is a poor predictor of adiposity changes over time</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatr</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12887-018-1160-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29880034?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29880034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0209746.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jurkowski</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Horan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orav</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kamdar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Correlates of resource empowerment among parents of children with overweight or obesity</article-title>. <source>Childhood Obesity</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/chi.2016.0136</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27875076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27875076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>