<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BMJ-UK</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bmj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The BMJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0959-8138</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1756-1833</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6349133</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30692103</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">mikb047931</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.l257</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Analysis</subject></subj-group><series-title>Solutions for Prevention and Control of Non-communicable Diseases </series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Life course approach to prevention and control of non-communicable diseases</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>Bente</given-names></name><role>director</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Julianne</given-names></name><role>technical officer</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rakovac</surname><given-names>Ivo</given-names></name><role>programme manager</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wickramasinghe</surname><given-names>Kremlin</given-names></name><role>technical officer</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hennis</surname><given-names>Anselm</given-names></name><role>director</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>Hai-Rim</given-names></name><role>director</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>Mychelle</given-names></name><role>director</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><role>programme manager</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berdzuli</surname><given-names>Nino</given-names></name><role>programme manager</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>Carina</given-names></name><role>programme manager</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>Manfred</given-names></name><role>coordinator</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Breda</surname><given-names>Jo&#x000e3;o</given-names></name><role>head of office</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Division of Non-communicable Diseases and Promoting Health through the Life-course, WHO Regional Office for Europe, Copenhagen, Denmark</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>WHO European Office for Prevention and Control of NCDs, Moscow, Russia</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>Department of Noncommunicable Diseases and Mental Health, WHO Pan American Health Organization (PAHO), Washington, DC, USA</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>Division of Noncommunicable Diseases and Health through the Life-course, WHO Western Pacific Region (WPRO), Manila, Philippines </aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>NCD Child Governing Council, American Academy of Pediatrics/Society for Adolescent Health and Medicine, Itasca, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to: B Mikkelsen <email xlink:href="mikkelsenb@who.int">mikkelsenb@who.int</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>364</volume><elocation-id>l257</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Published by the BMJ Publishing Group Limited. For permission to use (where not already granted under a licence) please go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://group.bmj.com/group/rights-licensing/permissions">http://group.bmj.com/group/rights-licensing/permissions</ext-link></copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>BMJ</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/igo/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution IGO License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/igo/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/igo/</ext-link>), which permits use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmj.l257.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>A successful approach to reducing the burden of non-communicable disease requires action at all stages of life, argue <bold>Bente Mikkelsen and colleagues</bold>
</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Many of the health problems we encounter in adulthood stem from our experiences early in life&#x02014;in some cases, even from before we are born.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The major non-communicable diseases (NCDs) (diabetes, cardiovascular diseases, cancer, chronic respiratory diseases, and mental disorders) are often associated with older age groups, but the evidence suggests that they affect people of all ages. Fifteen million deaths attributed to NCDs occur between the ages of 30 and 69 years and people from all age groups are vulnerable to the risk factors that contribute to NCDs.<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</p><p>NCD prevention is most effective when it targets a problem at its roots. Taking early, appropriate, timely, and collective action<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> is important if we are to reduce premature mortality related to NCDs by a third by 2030&#x02014;a sustainable development goal that has been affirmed through political declarations by heads of states and governments. A life course approach is an inclusive approach that considers the needs of all age groups and addresses NCD prevention and control in its earliest stages and is recommended in the World Health Organization&#x02019;s global action plan for prevention and control of NCDs.<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
</p><p>The life course approach is underpinned by evidence from a wide range of disciplines showing how NCDs are influenced by early life factors.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> It provides a comprehensive and sustainable framework for identifying key settings for interventions, knowledge translation, and a systems thinking approach.<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> WHO uses the theory as a basis for many of its strategies and recommendations.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
</p><p>In this article we outline how a life course approach can be used to inform implementation of NCD prevention and control. We consider life stages from preconception to old age, and ways in which transitions in stage of life present opportunities for promoting health. We draw primarily on work from the European Region of WHO, which made life course approaches a major part of Health 2020<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> and the regional framework for prevention and control of NCDs.<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Here we will cover recommendations and considerations within the stages of preconception through the periods of childhood, adolescence, and old age. Across the life course, WHO has recommendations for the prevention of NCDs that will affect all age groups,<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> and these are discussed in more detail in the appendix on bmj.com. To reduce NCDs, it is also crucial to tackle the upstream determinants of health. Health policies must include the unique challenges posed by poverty, such as poor housing conditions and lack of social security, which are associated with poor health outcomes. Public policy should be developed for a coordinated response to the structural and social determinants of health and exposure to unhealthy environments. </p><p>Although we focus on a national level, the principles and themes are applicable to cities, schools, workplaces, and other local settings. </p><sec sec-type="other1"><title>Stages of the life course</title><p>The main risk factors for non-communicable diseases are tobacco use, harmful use of alcohol, lack of physical activity, unhealthy diet, and air pollution. Throughout all stages of life, there are ways in which these risk factors may be targeted to help prevent the development of NCDs and mental health disorders later in life.</p><p>Priority interventions include both population and individual level activities. Population level interventions that have been identified as good value for money include regulations and taxations on tobacco and alcohol, promotion of healthy foods through transformed marketing policies, including improved packaging of commercial products, and revised fiscal strategies. Commercial products can be reformulated to reduce salt, saturated fats, and sugar consumption, and health literacy can be promoted by educating at-risk populations, so that they recognise the importance of healthy options. Active living and mobility can also be promoted.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Air pollution is responsible for millions of deaths each year, thus, clean air is an essential component of NCDs prevention.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Some of these interventions will be more relevant and efficient at certain stages of the life course, but most of them will affect people at all ages. The same is true for the interventions aimed at individuals, such as cardiometabolic risk assessment and management, early detection and effective treatment of major NCDs, and vaccination and relevant communicable disease control. </p><p>The life course approach is an intuitive way to conceptualise NCD prevention and control. It provides a comprehensive and sustainable framework to introduce key interventions for improved health literacy and knowledge translation. Additionally, it provides an avenue for adopting a complex systems model of public health.<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="other2"><title>Preconception and prenatal care</title><p>The preconception period refers to a woman&#x02019;s health before she becomes pregnant, and the prenatal period refers to the time from conception up to the child&#x02019;s birth. Evidence is growing that a woman&#x02019;s nutritional status during these periods may influence her offspring&#x02019;s health and susceptibility to NCDs later in life.<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</p><p>WHO recommends that before and during pregnancy, promoting healthy nutrition and regular physical activity can prevent hypertension and gestational diabetes.<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Unborn children are adversely affected by harmful exposures such as air pollution, tobacco use, and maternal consumption of alcohol.<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
</p><p>Focused public health policies and primary healthcare services promote access to quality services during the preconception phase. Essential interventions include monitoring weight and counselling on nutrition and exercise. These are essential components of primary healthcare, and linkages to maternal health systems can facilitate early access to prenatal care.<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> During pregnancy, health professionals should continue weight management and support physical activity, to improve the health of the mother and her child.<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
</p><p>Pregnancy presents an opportunity for family centred health promotion. Household members should be advised to eliminate tobacco use, to reduce alcohol consumption, and to eliminate air pollution within the home.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other3"><title>Infancy</title><p>Infancy is an extremely important stage for the prevention of NCDs later in life.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> A WHO systematic review of the literature concludes that a person&#x02019;s propensity to develop NCDs and obesity may be influenced during fetal development and infancy, and these factors may in part explain the observed correlation between health inequalities and NCDs.<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
</p><p>Exclusive breastfeeding prevents NCDs and helps ensure healthy newborn development, as outlined in a WHO systematic review.<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Public policy has a key role in promoting breastfeeding,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> including through national labour policies supporting universal paid maternity leave and requiring workplaces to provide suitable accommodation for breastfeeding mothers, such as appropriate breaks and facilities.<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> National efforts are also needed to restrict the inappropriate marketing of products that compete with breastfeeding.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</p><p>The health system should promote breastfeeding, as outlined in the baby friendly hospital initiative, as well as monitoring the child&#x02019;s growth and the micronutrient status of both mother and newborn<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> and providing behaviour change support related to physical activity, diet, or substance use, where necessary.</p><p>Infancy is also a key time for providing vaccinations, including hepatitis B vaccinations to protect against liver cancer.<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
</p><p>A crucial consideration here is the child&#x02019;s environment&#x02014;in the home, in day care centres, or in nursery facilities. In structuring these environments, a primary aim is to mitigate the infant&#x02019;s exposure to harmful influences such as secondary tobacco smoke, air pollution, and other environmental toxins.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other4"><title>Childhood</title><p>Children are exposed to multiple settings where new NCD related risks may be encountered. Kindergartens, schools, and preschools are perhaps the most important, partly because most children experience them and partly because they are a good setting for health promotion activities. </p><p>Physical activity and a healthy diet in childhood are prerequisites for healthy development. It is therefore important to structure children&#x02019;s environments in ways that result in sufficiently high physical activity levels and low levels of consumption of energy dense, nutrient poor foods.<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Health promoting schools, nurseries, or kindergartens can design their environments and practices in ways that steer children towards greater fruit and vegetable consumption and increased physical activity.<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Additionally, it is important to provide opportunities for children to actively travel to school such as safe footpaths and cycle lanes.<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
</p><p>Policy makers should also consider creating national standards for the food and drinks available in schools, placing restrictions on the marketing of unhealthy foods (including social marketing), mandating smoke-free childcare facilities, or monitoring the air in schools and public recreational settings to ensure that they meet WHO indoor air quality guidelines.<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
</p><p>Schools are also a good place to monitor risk factors for NCDs, and the data can be used to guide national prevention policies.. For example, the WHO European Childhood Obesity Surveillance Initiative measures trends in overweight and obesity among primary schoolchildren in more than 40 European countries, ensuring the availability of high quality data to inform policy and practice, and to respond to the problem of childhood overweight and obesity.<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="other5"><title>Adolescence</title><p>Adolescence, defined as the transitional phase between childhood and adulthood, is a time when young people begin developing habits that will carry over into adulthood and have large implications for their NCD risk. At this age, important settings for health promotion include healthy school environments (described above), home environments, the neighbourhood on the journey to and from school, and afterschool clubs and sports clubs.</p><p>Adolescents are vulnerable to marketing of harmful substances such as alcohol and tobacco.<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Countries must strengthen implementation of the WHO Framework Convention on Tobacco Control and tackle emerging risks such as electronic nicotine delivery systems.<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Mental health also becomes increasingly important during adolescence,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> and prevention of bullying and provision of school based counselling are vital.<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
</p><p>Healthy behaviours initiated in childhood, such as physical activity and healthy nutrition, should be maintained during adolescence.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> A priority for policy should be to develop a coordinated response to the structural and social determinants of adolescent obesity,<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> food insecurity,<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> poor access to healthful food, and exposure to unhealthy environments. Although it is important at all stages of life,<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> health literacy is highly valuable in adolescence as young people begin to make their own decisions related to their health. Finally, provision of HPV vaccinations to adolescent girls has been shown to be cost effective as part of a comprehensive approach to cervical cancer prevention.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</p><p>To inform policy action, it is important to collect information about individual risk factor behaviours, as well as information about the implementation and effectiveness of health promotion interventions.<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> The Health Behaviour in School Aged Children<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> initiative is a useful guide to measuring NCD risk factors during these important years.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other6"><title>Adulthood</title><p>The workplace is an important setting for health promotion during adulthood.<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Interventions that have been shown to be effective include promoting healthy food options in canteens and by offering nutrition education and counselling.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Workplace policies restricting alcohol and tobacco use are important for the health of all employees. Providing opportunities and incentives for physical activity (including active transport) can promote mental health, prevent and rehabilitate musculoskeletal disorders, and improve heart health.<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
</p><p>Policies to improve health behaviours only through workplace settings will exclude groups most likely to have NCDs, such as unemployed people. To ensure that interventions do not widen inequalities further, it is important to integrate similar health promoting interventions in other accessible settings, including community centres, churches, healthcare settings, rehabilitation centres, and recreational facilities.</p><p>Among the many opportunities for improving NCD related surveillance during adulthood, monitoring alcohol and tobacco use is particularly important for purposes of targeting interventions, monitoring progress, and advocacy.<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Patterns related to tobacco and alcohol use, physical activity, and nutrition among adults should be measured alongside socioeconomic, demographic, or geographical variables. Population based surveillance can strengthen targeted cost effective approaches to NCD prevention and early intervention.</p><p>Governments can introduce various policies to reduce NCDs in adulthood. Fiscal policies, for instance, could tax unhealthy products such as tobacco, alcohol, or sugary drinks, and fund schemes that subsidise fruit and vegetables.<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Policies that promote mental health, such as strengthening leadership and governance and providing comprehensive mental health and social care services, are also beneficial at a time when people may face unsatisfying careers, unemployment, financial stressors, low social engagement, divorce, or poor emotional resilience.<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
</p><p>Health systems can support adults by providing universal healthcare and mental health services, screening services,<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> brief interventions targeting NCD risk factors in primary care,<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> and access to affordable drugs for the prevention and control of NCDs.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="other7"><title>Older people</title><p>The transition from working adulthood into retirement presents unique opportunities for promoting health as people find new ways to spend their time and resources, while also facing changing identities and relationships.<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> It is important that as people leave the workplace, they continue to have access to support from other settings, including community centres, primary healthcare programmes, assisted living facilities, hospitals, and home care services. Measures should be taken to maintain functional capacity, strength, and balance of older people<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> and promote nutrition for older people with diet related NCDs and micronutrient deficiencies.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</p><p>Mental health must also be targeted&#x02014;for example, through policies ensuring social support at a time when people often experience social isolation, bereavement, discrimination, financial stress.<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> This support is often provided at the local level and in cooperation with volunteering activities. Communities must provide appropriate environments for physical activity among older people such as safe neighbourhoods, infrastructure for walking and cycling, and access to recreation facilities,<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> as well as involving older people in wider social physical activities.</p><p>Many surveillance schemes for NCDs exclude older people, and it is worth finding ways to include people older than 69, particularly in the face of ageing populations. Having access to high quality data on NCDs and their risk factors among older people could provide insights for evaluating trends, targeting health promotion interventions, and monitoring the effectiveness of policies aimed to improve the health of older people. </p><p>Health systems can ensure promotion of physical activity and healthy nutrition in healthcare settings and residential homes and promote physical activity and nutrition by improving the quality of advice that health professionals give to older people.<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>A life course approach is an underused way to approach NCD prevention and control. Unlike a disease oriented approach, which focuses on interventions for a single condition, a life course approach considers the critical stages, transitions, and settings where large differences can be made in promoting or restoring health. Importantly, it takes into account the social determinants of health, gender, equity, and human rights. It has been emphasised in numerous frameworks and initiatives in the past decade, but more work is needed to give the approach more prominence. Ensuring that the life course perspective is integrated more fully into our work will help us identify appropriate settings for health promotion, design more effective interventions, and ultimately, save lives. </p><p>Taking a life course approach requires that we improve health literacy through multisectoral work with individuals, institutions, communities, and countries. Interventions must extend beyond the health sector and be targeted within the natural settings that people encounter through the various stages of their lives. Taking this life course approach will help us to achieve SDG 3.4 and reduce premature mortality by 30% before 2030.</p><boxed-text id="boxa" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Key messages</title></caption><p>&#x02022; Through political declarations, heads of states and governments have committed to reduce premature deaths by 30% before 2030.</p><p>&#x02022; A set of cost effective and affordable policy options (best buys) exist to tackle NCDs</p><p>&#x02022;Interventions to reduce risk from non-communicable diseases should be applied through the lifecourse. </p><p>&#x02022; Actions targeted at one life stage often also influence health behaviour and outcomes at other stages</p><p>&#x02022; The life course approach can help determine when and how to influence the social determinants of health</p></boxed-text></sec></body><back><notes notes-type="data-supplement"><label>Web Extra</label><p>Extra material supplied by the author</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><caption><p><?igo-by?>Appendix 1: Thinking across the life course</p></caption><media xlink:href="mikb047931.ww1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e595" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></notes><notes><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Competing interests:<?igo-by?> We have read and understood BMJ policy on declaration of interests and have no relevant interests to declare. The authors alone are responsible for the views expressed in this article and they do not necessarily represent the decisions, policy, or views of the World Health Organization.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Provenance and peer review: Commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>This article is part of a series proposed by the WHO Global Coordination Mechanism on NCDs and commissioned by <italic>The BMJ</italic>, which peer reviewed, edited, and made the decision to publish. Open access fees are funded by WHO.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>For other articles in the series see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bmj.com/NCD-solutions">www.bmj.com/NCD-solutions</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group></notes><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. The Minsk Declaration: the life-course approach in the context of health 2020. WHO, 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A life course approach to chronic disease epidemiology</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Public Health</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.publhealth.26.021304.144505</pub-id>&#x000a0;
<?supplied-pmid 15760279?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15760279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Life course health care and preemptive approach to non-communicable diseases</article-title>. <source>Proc Jpn Acad Ser B Phys Biol Sci</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>462</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2183/pjab.89.462</pub-id>&#x000a0;
<?supplied-pmid 24334510?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24334510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">World Health Organization. Tackling NCDs: Best buys and other recommended interventions for the prevention and control of noncommunicable diseases. WHO, 2017. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/ncds/management/best-buys/en/">https://www.who.int/ncds/management/best-buys/en/</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. European action plan to reduce the harmful use of alcohol 2012-2020. WHO, 2012;</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>
<source>European food and nutrition action plan 2015-2020.</source>
<publisher-name>WHO Europe</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">World Health Organization. Good maternal nutrition the best start in life. WHO, 2016. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0008/313667/Good-maternal-nutrition-The-best-start-in-life.pdf?ua=1">http://www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0008/313667/Good-maternal-nutrition-The-best-start-in-life.pdf?ua=1</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>
<source>Physical activity strategy for the WHO European region 2016-2025.</source>
<publisher-name>WHO Europe</publisher-name>, <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>
<source>Prevention and control of noncommunicable diseases: guidelines for primary health care in low resource settings.</source>
<publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>, <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Noncommunicable Diseases: Key facts. 2018. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/noncommunicable-diseases">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/noncommunicable-diseases</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Global Action Plan for the Prevention and Control of NCDs 2013-2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/nmh/events/ncd_action_plan/en/">https://www.who.int/nmh/events/ncd_action_plan/en/</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>DJP</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Mothers, babies and health in later life.</source>
<publisher-name>Elsevier Health Sciences</publisher-name>, <year>1998</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>GMV</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Life-course approach in the control and prevention of chronic diseases.</source>
<publisher-name>Available from</publisher-name>, <year>2018</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bmj.com/rapid-response/2011/11/03/life-course-approach-control-and-prevention-chronic-diseases">https://www.bmj.com/rapid-response/2011/11/03/life-course-approach-control-and-prevention-chronic-diseases</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Savona</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Glonti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The need for a complex systems model of evidence for public health</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>390</volume>:<fpage>2602</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(17)31267-9</pub-id>&#x000a0;
<?supplied-pmid 28622953?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28622953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group>
<source>Report of the commission on ending childhood obesity.</source>
<publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>, <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Shanghai declaration on promoting health in the 2030 agenda for sustainable development. WHO, 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">World Health Organization. Vienna declaration on nutrition and noncommunicable diseases in the context of health 2020. 2013. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0005/193253/CONSENSUS-Vienna-Declaration-5-July-2013.pdf">http://www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0005/193253/CONSENSUS-Vienna-Declaration-5-July-2013.pdf</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>
<source>World report on ageing and health.</source>
<publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>, <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">World Health Organization. Health 2020: the European policy for health and wellbeing. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/health-policy/health-2020-the-european-policy-for-health-and-well-being">http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/health-policy/health-2020-the-european-policy-for-health-and-well-being</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Action plan for the prevention and control of noncommunicable diseases in the WHO European Region. WHO Europe, 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Ambient air pollution: health impacts <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/airpollution/ambient/health-impacts/en/">https://www.who.int/airpollution/ambient/health-impacts/en/</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Savona</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Glonti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The need for a complex systems model of evidence for public health</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>390</volume>:<fpage>2602</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(17)31267-9</pub-id>&#x000a0;
<?supplied-pmid 28622953?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28622953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Tobacco-free generations: protecting children from tobacco in the WHO European Region. WHO Europe, 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Good maternal nutrition the best start in life</article-title>. <year>2016</year>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/disease-prevention/nutrition/publications/2016/good-maternal-nutrition.-the-best-start-in-life-2016">http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/disease-prevention/nutrition/publications/2016/good-maternal-nutrition.-the-best-start-in-life-2016</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hutin Y, Desai S, Bulterys M. Preventing hepatitis B virus infection: milestones and targets. <italic>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</italic> 2018;96:443-A.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Do attributes in the physical environment influence children&#x02019;s physical activity? A review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1479-5868-3-19</pub-id>&#x000a0;
<?supplied-pmid 16872543?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16872543</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. WHO European Childhood Obesity Surveillance. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/disease-prevention/nutrition/activities/who-european-childhood-obesity-surveillance-initiative-cosi">http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/disease-prevention/nutrition/activities/who-european-childhood-obesity-surveillance-initiative-cosi</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pechmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Loughlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Impulsive and self-conscious: Adolescents&#x02019; vulnerability to advertising and promotion</article-title>. <source>J Public Policy Mark</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>202</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1509/jppm.2005.24.2.202</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Flisher</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hetrick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McGorry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mental health of young people: a global public-health challenge</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>369</volume>:<fpage>1302</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)60368-7</pub-id>&#x000a0;
<?supplied-pmid 17434406?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17434406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">World Health Organization (EURO). The health and well-being of men in the WHO European Region: better health through a gender approach. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/health-determinants/gender/publications/2018/the-health-and-well-being-of-men-in-the-who-european-region-better-health-through-a-gender-approach-2018">http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/health-determinants/gender/publications/2018/the-health-and-well-being-of-men-in-the-who-european-region-better-health-through-a-gender-approach-2018</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Inchley J. Adolescent obesity and related behaviours: trends and inequalities in the WHO European region, 2002-2014: Observations from the Health Behavior in School-aged Children (HBSC) WHO Collaborative Cross-national Study. WHO Europe, 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">WHO. <source>Investing in children: The European child and adolescent health strategy 2015-2020.</source>
<publisher-name>WHO Europe</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>DER</given-names></name><name><surname>Bredin</surname><given-names>SSD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Health benefits of physical activity: a systematic review of current systematic reviews</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cardiol</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>541</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HCO.0000000000000437</pub-id>&#x000a0;
<?supplied-pmid 28708630?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28708630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marten</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadandale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/><collab>Sugar, Tobacco, and Alcohol Taxes (STAX) Group</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Sugar, tobacco, and alcohol taxes to achieve the SDGs</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>391</volume>:<fpage>2400</fpage>-<lpage>1</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)31219-4</pub-id>&#x000a0;
<?supplied-pmid 29858115?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29858115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thow</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Trevena</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Waqanivalu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cawley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Fiscal policy to improve diets and prevent noncommunicable diseases: from recommendations to action</article-title>. <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2471/BLT.17.195982</pub-id>&#x000a0;
<?supplied-pmid 29531419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29531419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">National Institute on Aging. The health &#x00026; retirement study. National Institutes of Health, US Department of Health &#x00026; Human Resources. 2012. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hrsonline.isr.umich.edu/">http://hrsonline.isr.umich.edu/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>
<source>Age-friendly environments in Europe: A handbook of domains for policy action.</source> WHO, <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>